<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon preached the 26. day of May. 1584. in S. Maries Church in Shrewesbury before the right honorable the Earle of Leicester, accompanied with the Earle of Essex, the Lorde North, diuers knightes, gentle-men of worshypfull callyng, the worshipfull bayliues, aldermen and burgesses of the towne of Salop. By Iohn Tomkys publick preacher of Gods word there: now first published by the authour. Seen, perused, and allowed accordyng to her Maiesties iniunctions.</title>
            <author>Tomkys, John.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1586</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 140 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 49 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A13809</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 24110</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S118479</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99853686</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99853686</idno>
            <idno type="VID">19080</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A13809)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 19080)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 361:3)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon preached the 26. day of May. 1584. in S. Maries Church in Shrewesbury before the right honorable the Earle of Leicester, accompanied with the Earle of Essex, the Lorde North, diuers knightes, gentle-men of worshypfull callyng, the worshipfull bayliues, aldermen and burgesses of the towne of Salop. By Iohn Tomkys publick preacher of Gods word there: now first published by the authour. Seen, perused, and allowed accordyng to her Maiesties iniunctions.</title>
                  <author>Tomkys, John.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[96] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Robert Waldegraue, for Wiliam Ponsonby,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>At London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Anno. 1586.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signatures: [A] B-F.</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: A sermon preached at Shrewesburie.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  16th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:19080:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:19080:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A SERMON <hi>Preached the</hi> 26. <hi>day of</hi> May. 1584. in S. Maries Church <hi>in Shrewesbury: Before the right honora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble</hi> the Earle of Leiceſter, accompanied with the Earle of Eſſex, the Lorde North, di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers Knightes; Gentle-men of wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhypfull callyng, the worſhipfull Bayliues, Aldermen and Burgeſſes of the towne of Salop.</p>
            <p>By Iohn Tomkys publick prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher of Gods word there: <hi>Now firſt publiſhed by the authour.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>Iam. 3.2.</bibl>
               <p>In many thynges we of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend all.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>Seen, peruſed, and allowed accordyng to her Maieſties Iniunctions.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>AT LONDON, Printed by Robert Walde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>graue, for William Ponſonby. Anno. 1586.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:19080:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:19080:2"/>
            <head>
               <hi>¶To the right honoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble,</hi> the Lord ROBERT DVDLEY <hi>Earle of</hi> Leyceſter, <hi>&amp;c. one of her high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes</hi> moſt honourable priuy Counſayle, and Chancellor of the Vniuerſitie of Oxford, grace mercy and peace, in Chriſt Ieſus be multiplied.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Haue bene reque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted (right honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable) by one, whoſe motion, in honeſt cauſes, is vnto me as a commandement, to beſtowe vpon him that ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple Sermon, which by Gods aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtaunce, I made before your Lordſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ip in S. Maryes Church <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ewesbury, the 26. of May <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>584. Although my maner haue bene hetherto, for the moſt part
<pb facs="tcp:19080:3" rendition="simple:additions"/> rather to delyuer vnto the Church, through my laborious tranſlations, the learning of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, then, in this learned age, to offer to publique viewe, myne own poore trauels: yet becauſe the aucthority of the requeſter, then one of my hearers, was ſo great, and his wiſedom ſo graue that it ſtoode with dutifull mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſtie, rather to yeeld than to deny, I foorthwith called my ſelfe to remembraunce, what I had vttered (as God vouchſafed to inhable me) and committed the ſame to writing, as leiſure did ſerue me. My trauayle again by me peruſed, ſeemed in mine eies ſo ſeelie, that caſting it a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide as an vntimely bearthe, hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therto I haue detracted the performaunce of my promiſe<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> But nowe conſidering that a
<pb facs="tcp:19080:3"/> promiſe aduiſedly made, may not raſhly be broken, I find my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe in duety forced, to do that, which in Chriſtianitie, I was then required. And, acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledging it my duetie, to vſe my tongue and my penne, rather to the benefit of my country, then the winning of credite, I haue boldly reſolued, ſo to keep pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe, that the good of my ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon, by the benefite of the print, may become common to al the godly. Although the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter therein contained be warra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by Gods word, and the do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine therin taught be neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie for the tyme, yet, becauſe the maner of the deliuerie there-of is homely and baſe, it is altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther vnworthy in your L. name to be publiſhed, who worthely are become a patron of the
<pb facs="tcp:19080:4"/> workes of the beſt learned. Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uertheleſſe, ſince your Lordſhip in this my labour hath the beſt intereſt, becauſe except you had vouchſafed that time to haue heard me, I had not that daye ſpoken (being no ordinary day of my weekly exerciſe) and, that it pleaſed you of your ſingular humanitie, to prooue my duti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full indeuour, I make bolde in humbleneſſe, to offer that nowe to your eyes, which in dutiful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe I ſounded then in your eares. If I were able to deliuer vnto you a more worthy mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nument of my duetifull thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe, for the manifold bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fites by me vndeſerued, which vpon me you haue largely be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowed, verely I would be infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riour to none of your debters in will, which haue them all my
<pb facs="tcp:19080:4" rendition="simple:additions"/> ſuperiours in habilitie. And therefore I hope your H. wil ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept that which I can, ſeeing I cannot that which I would. Our memory cannot commit to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuion, how curteouſly you ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted that meane, and yet wel meant intertainmenr, which the towne of Shrewsburie in dutie gaue vnto you L. And the po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteritie, no doubt, ſhall heare of your thankefull accepting of many wel-comes, your cheerful hearing of many orations, your circumſpect view of the ſituati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and buildings of the towne, your graue conference with the Magiſtrates in the gouernment there of: your comfortable go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing into the free Grammer ſchoole, to experience the to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardlineſſe of the youth there, your Chriſtian preſence in the
<pb facs="tcp:19080:5" rendition="simple:additions"/> Church at the Sermon, your painefull trauell in arbitrating controuerſies, your large giftes vnto maiſter Bayliffes officers, your liberall rewardes vnto the ſcholemaiſters, your charitable almes vnto the poore, all the whiche vertues did then ſhine in you, as in a moſte cleare mir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour of true nobilitie. Neither did you forget in that your pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſe, that you, with the reſt of Gods children in earth, are ſtrangers and paſſengers in this world,<note n="(a)" place="margin">Gen 47.9.</note> as our fathers were,<note n="(b)" place="margin">Heb. 13.14.</note> which <hi>haue not here a continuing citie, but ſeeke one to come.</hi> Therefore as a prouident peregrine, you carefully tooke your ſpirituall repaſt, in euery of your manſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, in feeding vpon the worde of God preached before you, for the better refreſhing of the
<pb facs="tcp:19080:5"/> ſoule. In this your chriſtian per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taking of the heauenly foode, it pleaſed GOD of his gracious prouidence, aboue myne expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctation, to vouchſafe, that I did twiſe ſerue at his ſpiritual table, once in the countie of Stafford, where I was borne, and once in Shrewſburie, where I haue my charge, The diſhes, whiche I offered to the geſtes, were not dainty (I do co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>feſſe) yet becauſe they were wholeſome and ſauo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, being well ſeaſoned with the ſalte of Gods word, I make bold vnder your honourable prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, to offer the one of them to the taſte of the godly, that by this meanes the feaſt may be ſtill continued. I doubt not, but they will take it in good part, which haue learned, that God,<note n="(a)" place="margin">1. King. 19.6.</note> which fed ELIAS with <hi>bread</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:19080:6" rendition="simple:additions"/> and <hi>water,</hi>
               <note n="(a)" place="margin">Ioh. 6.11.</note> and refreſhed hys people with <hi>barly loues</hi> and <hi>ſmall fiſhes,</hi> will, that wee craue at hys handes not dayntie,<note n="(b)" place="margin">Mat. 6.13 Luc. 11.3.</note> but <hi>dayly bread,</hi> contenting our ſelues with homely, yet wholeſome foode. From others, (if there be any, as I doubt there be manie) whoſe taſte is ſo curious, that they will not, or ſtomacke ſo lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, that they cannot find any ſweetneſſe in the word of God,<note n="(c)" place="margin">Deut. 8.3. Mat. 4.4. Luc. 4.4.</note> whiche is the foode of the ſoule, I expect no ſuche thing, but referring them to the Lord, I humbly deſire him of his mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, (if it be his will) ſo to purifie their heartes, by the operation of his ſpirite,<note n="(d)" place="margin">Pſal. 34.9</note> that they may <hi>taſte</hi> and <hi>ſee, how good the Lordis.</hi>
               <note n="(e)" place="margin">Luc. 14.15.</note> So ſhall wee be <hi>bleſſed, eating our bread in the kingdome of God.</hi> God long preſerue your honour, and
<pb facs="tcp:19080:6" rendition="simple:additions"/> ſo guide you with his holy ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rite, that you may more and more ſet foorth his glory, bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fite hys Churche: and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit your Country. Salop the 24. of October. 1585.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your honours moste duetifull bound in the Lord. <hi>IOHN TOMKYS.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:19080:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:19080:7"/>
            <head>
               <hi>A Sermon preached in</hi> Shrewesburie, before the Earle <hi>of Leiceſter, by Iohn Tomkys,</hi> the 26. of May, 1584.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>Epheſians. 5.1.2.</bibl>
                  <p>
                     <note n="(a)" place="margin">Eph. 5.1.2</note>Be ye therefore followers of GOD, as deare children, And walke in loue, euen as Chriſt hath loued vs, to be an offering and a ſacrifice of a ſweete ſmelling ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour to God.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <note n="*" place="margin">The care of God for his people,</note>
               <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg>Vr heauenly <hi>father</hi> is ſo carefull for our ſpirituall ſuſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naunce (right hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable, worſhypfull, and dearely beloued in the <hi>Lord</hi>) that hee giueth vs, not onely his bleſſed worde, to become<note n="(a)" place="margin">Deu. 8.3. Mat. 4.4. Luc. 4.4.</note> the foode of the ſoule, but alſo<note n="(b)" place="margin">Mat. 22.</note> faythfull Miniſters to breake vnto vs the ſame. Hee ſent vnto his aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient
<pb facs="tcp:19080:8" rendition="simple:additions"/> people, deſcended from <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braham</hi> the <hi>Patriarche</hi> according to the fleſhe, his holy <hi>Prophetes,</hi>
               <note n="(a)" place="margin">Eſa. 1.1. Ier. 1.1. Ezech. 1.1. Oſe. 1.1. Amos. 1.1. Abdi. 1.1. Hab. 1.1. Ag. 1.1. Zach. 1.1. Mal. 1.1.</note> 
               <note n="*" place="margin">The ſu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>me of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phetes do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine. Ier. 7.21.22.</note> to expounde the lawe to them,<note n="(b)" place="margin">Eſa. 5.11.</note> to denounce his curſes to the obſtinate,<note n="(c)" place="margin">Pſal. 1.1.</note> to publiſhe his bleſſinges to the pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitent, and<note n="(d)" place="margin">Ier. 31.31</note> to foreſhewe the newe couenaunt betweene <hi>God</hi> and <hi>Man</hi> in <hi>Chriſte</hi> the <hi>Mesſias</hi> then to come<note n="(e)" place="margin">Eſa. 8.1. Hab. 2.2.</note> And the ſame <hi>Prophets,</hi> by the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinct of <hi>Gods holy ſpirite,</hi> commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to writing, for the inſtruction of the poſteritie, the ſumme of the deuine Sermons, which they preached to the people. Hee hath ſent vnto his newe people,<note n="(f)" place="margin">Io. 11.16. Rom. 3.29.</note> gathered to geather of the beleeuing <hi>Iewes</hi> and beleeuing <hi>Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles,</hi> thorowe faith in <hi>Chriſt</hi> his <hi>Son,</hi> his bleſſed <hi>Apoſtles</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">The ſu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>me of the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine.</note> 
               <note n="(g)" place="margin">Mat. 28.19.20. Mar. 16.15. Act. 2.38.</note> to preach re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentaunce for the remiſſion of ſinnes,<note n="(h)" place="margin">Rom. 6.1 &amp;c.</note> to teache newnes of life to the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of <hi>God,</hi>
               <note n="(i)" place="margin">Heb. 4.12</note> and to teſtifie the perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance of the new couenant between <hi>God</hi> and <hi>Man,</hi> in <hi>Chriſt</hi> the <hi>Mesſias</hi> in their time exhibited. And leaſt the Church of <hi>God</hi>
               <note n="(k)" place="margin">Num. 12.17. 1. Cor. 4.1.</note> which is his houſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houlde, ſhould want the leaſt crumbe
<pb facs="tcp:19080:8" rendition="simple:additions"/> of his heauenly foode, the ſame <hi>holie ſpirite</hi> hath mooued the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> and <hi>Diſciples</hi> of <hi>Chriſt,</hi>
               <note n="(a)" place="margin">Io. 20.31 Reuel. 1.19.</note> to recorde in writing the hiſtorie, doctrine, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſies of the newe couenaunt. Soe bountiful a <hi>Father</hi> is our <hi>God,</hi> which giueth vs plentie of heauenly, foode, ſo prouident a <hi>Lord</hi> is he whiche ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth vs from age to age faithfull diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſers thereof.</p>
            <p>
               <note n="*" place="margin">The ſu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>me of Gods word.</note>The ſumme of the whole word of <hi>God,</hi> ſo gratiouſly giuen, ſo faithfully taught, and ſo neceſſarilie written, is contained in two pointes: true fayth, and godly life.</p>
            <p>
               <note n="*" place="margin">The me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thode of the Epiſtle to the Epheſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans.</note>The <hi>Apoſtle Paule</hi> hath exactlie obſerued this methode in this his hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly Epiſtle written to the <hi>Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans</hi> of <hi>Epheſus.</hi> For in the firſt three chapters hee prooueth that we are<note n="(b)" place="margin">Rom. 3.20:28.</note> iuſtified not by our <hi>workes,</hi>
               <note n="(c)" place="margin">Lu. 17.5.</note> but by <hi>faith,</hi> which is the<note n="(d)" place="margin">Ephe. 2.8</note> 
               <hi>Gift of God.</hi> And in the three laſt chapters he ſheweth, that works be neceſſary, becauſe they are the<note n="(e)" place="margin">Gal. 5.22</note> fruites of faith,<note n="(f)" place="margin">Iam. 2.18</note> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by our profeſſion is adorned,<note n="(g)" place="margin">Mat. 5.16</note> and <hi>God</hi> glorified: O that this leſſon were
<pb facs="tcp:19080:9"/> as well practiſed, as it may eaſely be learned, then ſhould we be,<note n="(a)" place="margin">Ia. 1.22.</note> 
               <hi>not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly hearers of the worde, but doers of the ſame.</hi> The <hi>Apoſtle</hi> hauyng taught this doctrine to the <hi>Epheſians,</hi> and that moſt plentifully, for the ſpace of<note n="(b)" place="margin">Act. 20.31.</note> three yeares, and being therefore become<note n="(c)" place="margin">Epheſ. 3.1.</note> a priſoner in <hi>Rome,</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitteth to writing the ſumme of his doctrine, for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> confirmation of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> faith of the <hi>Epheſians,</hi> &amp; the inſtruction of the ages to come. Herein he imitateth the auncient <hi>Prophetes</hi> whoſe maner was briefly<note n="(d)" place="margin">Eſa. 8.1. Abac. 2.2.</note> to put in writing, that whiche largely they taught. Such loue bare <hi>Paul</hi> to the flocke of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> ſo perfect a paterne is hee of a godly paſtor. Now, for ſomuch as it is ſo ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarie to learne to beleue aright,<note n="(e)" place="margin">Act. 13.39. Rom 3.28.</note> that <hi>thereby</hi> we may be <hi>iustified,</hi> and to liue a right,<note n="(f)" place="margin">Mat. 5.16.</note> that <hi>thereby <hi>God</hi>
               </hi> may be <hi>glorified,</hi> I eſteemed this text very fitte for this auditorie, becauſe therein the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> briefly co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>prehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth both thoſe pointes, although in an altered order<note n="*" place="margin">The diſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bution of the text.</note> firſt ſpeaking of life, and then of fayth. If the profeſſion of
<pb facs="tcp:19080:9"/> 
               <hi>Chriſtians</hi> were nothing els but an idle ſpeculation, then were it ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what to be able to talke <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Religion, although wee liued not religiouſly. But <hi>Chriſt,</hi> the authour of truth, and the wiſedome of his heauenly <hi>father,</hi> hath taught vs, that<note n="(a)" place="margin">Mat. 7.21.22.23.</note> 
               <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ayn we call him our <hi>Lord,</hi> except <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> wil of his <hi>father</hi>
               </hi> reuealed vnto <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> his word: &amp; <hi>Iames,</hi> as a faithfull do<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>r in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſchole of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> exhorteth vs to<note n="(b)" place="margin">Iam. 1.22</note> 
               <hi>be doers of the word, &amp; not hearers onely deceiuyng our ſelues:</hi> what greater care the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ought <hi>Chriſtians</hi> to haue, than by their god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly liues to make their holy conuerſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to ſhine in the world to the glorye of <hi>God,</hi> the edifying of his Churche, &amp; to the teſtimonie in their owne con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences, that they be his children?</p>
            <p>
               <note n="*" place="margin">The vſe of Gods lawe,</note>And leſt wee ſhould wander out of the way of righteouſnes, by framing vnto our ſelues a fayth according to our fooliſhe fantaſies, or a life agrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to our curious imaginatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, <hi>God</hi> hath giuen vs his lawe<note n="(c)" place="margin">Pſal. 1.2.</note> 
               <hi>to meditate therein both day and night.</hi> Yea, and that we may bee effectually ſtirred vp
<pb facs="tcp:19080:10" rendition="simple:additions"/> to <hi>ſerue</hi> our heauenly <hi>Father without feare,</hi>
               <note n="a" place="margin">Luc. 1.74.75.</note> 
               <hi>in holineſſe and righteouſneſſe before him all the dayes of our life,</hi> hee dealeth with vs in his word diuerſly. For ſometimes hee<note n="b" place="margin">Deu. 11.27.</note> promiſeth his bleſſinges to vs, if we obey his ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutes: Sometimes he<note n="c" place="margin">28.</note> threatneth his curſes, if we tranſgreſſe his ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naunces: ſometimes he<note n="d" place="margin">Eſa. 1.2.</note> prouoketh vs with the remembraunce of his be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefites beſtowed vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vs: Sometimes he<note n="e" place="margin">Pro. 3.11. Heb. 12.5. &amp;c. Imitation.</note> chaſteneth vs with his fatherly correction for our ame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dement. Vnto theſe and many other meanes of our inſtruction, ſet forth vnto vs in <hi>Gods</hi> word, S. <hi>Paule</hi> in this place addeth the very example of <hi>God</hi> himſelfe, to be imitated by vs: exhorting vs to be<note n="f" place="margin">Eph. 5.1.</note> 
               <hi>followers of God, as deare children.</hi> Herein appeareth the godly diſcretio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the <hi>Apoſtle,</hi> who wel conſidering y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we are as childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, not able to practiſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> preceptes of obedience, except we haue a paterne to imitate layd before vs, nurtereth vs by this meanes in the way of righteouſneſſe.</p>
            <p>* Now, that we erre not in this imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,
<pb facs="tcp:19080:10" rendition="simple:additions"/> taught by the <hi>Apoſtle,</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Foure things are to be obſerued in this imita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</note> we muſt carefully obſerue foure thinges. The firſt, <hi>Who is to be imitated:</hi> The ſecond, <hi>Why he</hi> (that is to be followed) <hi>is to be imitated:</hi> The third, <hi>Wherein he is to be imitated:</hi> The fourth: <hi>Of what maner that thyng is, wherein hee is to be imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tated.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note n="*" place="margin">1. God is to be imita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted.</note>
               <hi>Paule</hi> meaning to teache vs by imitation to leade a <hi>Chriſtian</hi> life, propoſeth <hi>God</hi> himſelfe to be <hi>imita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted</hi> by vs, Saying,<note n="a" place="margin">Epheſ 5.1.</note> 
               <hi>Be ye imitators of God.</hi> Herein we haue a mirror of <hi>Gods</hi> mercy towardes vs, which, as a louing <hi>Father,</hi> vouchſafeth to inſtruct vs his children, not onely by his word, but alſo by his owne exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple. If <hi>Poets</hi> haue ſpared no labour to imitate their <hi>Homer, Oratours,</hi> their <hi>Demoſthenes: Philoſophers,</hi> their <hi>Ariſtotle,</hi> that they might ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by attaine to ſome perfection in their own profeſſions, we <hi>Chriſtians</hi> may be abaſhed, yea rather by them con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned, if with all diligence we doe not imitate the moſte excellent and perfect paterne of <hi>God</hi> himſelfe.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:19080:11" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <note n="*" place="margin">God is to be immita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted three waies.</note>But ſince it is neither conueni, ent nor poſſible, that we the creatures ſhould imitate euery waye <hi>God</hi> the creator, who is<note n="(a)" place="margin">Eze. 10.5 Reuel. 11 17</note> infinite, and<note n="(b)" place="margin">Rom. 16.27. 1. Tim. 1.17</note> incomprehenſible, it is to be obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, that in his worde hee propoſeth himſelfe three wayes to be imitated:</p>
            <p>
               <note n="*" place="margin">1. in him ſelfe.</note>Firſt, <hi>in himſelfe.</hi> So did <hi>God</hi> ſet forth his holineſſe, as a paterne of holineſſe, to be practiſed by his anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent people the <hi>Iſraelites,</hi> when hee ſaid:<note n="(c)" place="margin">Leuit. 20.26.</note> 
               <hi>be ye holy vnto me, for I Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houah am holy, &amp; haue ſeuered you fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> other people, that yee ſhould be mine.</hi> And <hi>Chriſt</hi> our Sauiour, in his earneſt perſwaſion, which hee vſeth with his <hi>diſciples,</hi> to drawe them to the perfect practiſe of brotherly loue, (which then we ſhewe, when<note n="(d.)" place="margin">Mat. 5.44.</note> 
               <hi>wee loue our enimies, bleſſe them that curſe vs, do good to them that hate vs, and pray for them which hurt vs, and perſecute vs.</hi>)<note n="(e)" place="margin">48.</note> ſetteth forth to their imitation the perfect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of the loue of his heauenly <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther</hi> to man-kinde, which<note n="(f)" place="margin">45.</note> 
               <hi>maketh his ſunne to ariſe on the euil &amp; the good:
<pb facs="tcp:19080:11" rendition="simple:additions"/> and ſendeth rayne on the iuſt and vniuſt.</hi>
               <note n="(a)" place="margin">48.</note> 
               <hi>Yee ſhall therefore bee perfect</hi> (ſaith <hi>Chriſt) as your Father, which is in heauen, is perfect.</hi> The like may be obſerued, concerning the<note n="(b)" place="margin">Ro. 34.</note> truth of <hi>God,</hi> which he practiſeth in his promiſſes:<note n="(c)" place="margin">Pſa. 86.5</note> his mercie, which hee ſheweth to his ſeruants: His iuſtice:<note n="(d)" place="margin">145.17.</note> which appeareth in all his waies,<note n="(e)" place="margin">86.15. Rom. 2.4.</note> his longe ſufferance, whereby he prouoketh vs to repentance: All the which are paterns of trueth, of mercie, of iuſtice, and of patience by vs to bee vſed. And thus doth <hi>God</hi> propoſe him-ſelfe in him ſelfe to bee imitated of vs, as you haue heard.</p>
            <p>
               <note n="*" place="margin">.2. in his ſonne.</note>Secondly <hi>God</hi> ſetteth foorth himſelfe to bee <hi>imitated</hi> by vs in hys ſonne <hi>Chriſt Ieſus.</hi> Our heauenly <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther</hi> doth knowe the rudeneſſe of vs his children, who hardly can eſteeme him imitable, which by nature is a<note n="(f)" place="margin">Ioh. 4.24.</note> 
               <hi>Spirite</hi> inuiſible. Behold there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore his fatherly care to lead vs on in this holy imitation of him-ſelfe: Hee hath giuen vs his <hi>ſonne,</hi>
               <note n="(g)" place="margin">Heb. 1.3.</note> 
               <hi>who is the brighteneſſe of his glory, and the ingra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued
<pb facs="tcp:19080:12" rendition="simple:additions"/> forme of his perſon,</hi> which being by nature<note n="a" place="margin">Ioh. 17.5</note> 
               <hi>God</hi> with the <hi>Father,</hi>
               <note n="b" place="margin">Mat. 1.18.</note> is become <hi>man</hi> with vs,<note n="c" place="margin">Heb. 1.3.</note> in whoſe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward and ſubſtantiall brighteneſſe,<note n="d" place="margin">Ioh. 14.7.</note> (which we diſcerne by the effectes thereof in his viſible manhead) as it were in a glaſſe, we may behold, &amp; as it were handle, the infinit &amp; almighty maieſtie, the infinite &amp; incomprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible loue of <hi>God</hi> the <hi>Father,</hi> vnto vs his children through grace, that we might admire the one with all reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence, and imitate the other with all obedience.<note n="e" place="margin">Ioh. 14.9.</note> If we ſee <hi>Chriſt</hi> with the eyes of our faith, then ſee we the <hi>Father,</hi>
               <note n="f" place="margin">Heb. 1.3.</note> whoſe liuely image he is. Now,<note n="g" place="margin">Num. 21.9 Ioh. 3.14.8.56. heb. 11.13.</note> as <hi>Chriſt</hi> is beholden by a true faith,<note n="h" place="margin">Iam. 2.24.</note> ſo this fayth is made manifeſt by workes,<note n="i" place="margin">1. Cor. 11, .1</note> and thoſe workes muſt bee ſquared by the pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terne of the workes of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> in who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
               <hi>God</hi> ſetteth forth himſelfe to be imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tated.</p>
            <p>
               <note n="*" place="margin">The workes of Chriſt of two ſorts.</note>But becauſe the workes of <hi>Chriſt</hi> are of two ſortes: ſome miraculous, wrought in power<note n="k" place="margin">Ioh. 5.36.14.11.</note> to declare his <hi>Godhead,</hi> &amp; to confirme his doctrine:
<pb facs="tcp:19080:12" rendition="simple:additions"/> and ſome morall, wrought in obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence,<note n="a" place="margin">Mat. 5.17.</note> to ſhewe his <hi>Man-head,</hi> and to fulfill the lawe: wee muſt knowe that hee is to bee imitated in the laſt, and not in the firſt.</p>
            <p>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Miracles.</note>For ſeeing his <hi>Miracles</hi> were wrought to ſeale vp the trueth of his Doctrine, that hee might bee belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued,<note n="b." place="margin">Ioh. 14.11</note> for his workes ſake: and ſince hee hath ſufficienlie confirmed his doctrine, by the miracles wrought in his owne perſon by his abſolute power, and in the perſons of his <hi>Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles</hi> and <hi>Diſciples</hi> in the<note n="c." place="margin">Act. 3.16.</note> power of his name, it ſauoureth of infidelitie, (The gift of woorking of miracles being long a goe ceaſſed) to require of the Miniſters of the Goſpell, by miracles to prooue their Doctrine: and of preſumption, (without ſpeciall warrante from Gods <hi>ſpirite</hi>) to at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempte the working of anie miracle. The faithfull ſeruants therefore of the <hi>Lorde</hi> may not ſay to the ragyng ſea:<note n="d" place="margin">Mat. 4:39.</note> 
               <hi>Peace, bee thou ſtill:</hi> Nor to the ſicke of the palſie,<note n="e" place="margin">9, 6.</note> 
               <hi>Ariſe:</hi> Nor to the blind<note n="f" place="margin">Luc, 18, 42</note> 
               <hi>Receiue thy ſight:</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:19080:13" rendition="simple:additions"/> Nor to the leper<note n="(a)" place="margin">8.3.</note> 
               <hi>Bee thou cleane<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> Not to the buried in graue<note n="(b)" place="margin">10.11.43.</note> 
               <hi>Come forth.</hi> And if there bee anie other ſuch ſpeaches of <hi>Chriſt</hi> in the New Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, (as therebee manie) they can not aſſume them to themſelues with-out preſumption<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> why ſo? Forſooth, as they were woordes, which <hi>Chriſt</hi> vſed when he wrought his miracles, ſo are they mirrours of his Maieſtie, not to bee ſpoken by vs in imitation, but to bee reuerenced of vs in meditation. And how perilous a thing it is, to draw the miracles of <hi>Chriſt</hi> into imitation: the great abuſe of <hi>Lent</hi> in time of <hi>Pope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry</hi> doth ſufficiently declare. For to faſt fortie dayes &amp; fortie nightes, &amp; not to hungre, (<note n="(c)" place="margin">Mat. 4.2 Luke. 4.2.</note> as <hi>Chriſt</hi> did) ſo farre ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedeth the habilitie of man, that without miracle it was neuer pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſed of anie. And yet ſuch was the preſumption of the <hi>Romiſh</hi> Church, that it propoſed this miraculous and ſtraunge woorke of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taken by him for a preparitiue before hee begane to publiſh the Goſpell, as an example of imitation.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:19080:13" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <note n="*" place="margin">2. Conuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation.</note>The Newe Teſtament is the written recorde of the Doctrine and woorkes of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> wherein with all diligence wee muſt meditate, if wee will become followers of <hi>Chriſt</hi> in his Doctrine and life<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> whatſo euer we finde there written of his<note n="(a)" place="margin">Io. 3.17.</note> zeale to promote <hi>Gods</hi> glorie, of his<note n="(b)" place="margin">6.43.</note> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtancie in mayntaynyng the trueth, of his<note n="(c)" place="margin">11.35. &amp; 38.</note> pittie towardes the affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted, of his<note n="(d)" place="margin">1. Pet. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.23.</note> pacience in afflictions, of his<note n="(e)" place="margin">Mat. 11.29.</note> meekenes in his behauiour, of his<note n="(f)" place="margin">Ioh. 6.9.</note> ſobrietie in his diete, and of<note n="(g)" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. Pet. 2.22.</note> his modeſtie in all his life, that ſame is therefor written, to ſterre vs vp by his example, to expreſſe the like vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues in our conuerſation. Surelie, ſince<note n="(h)" place="margin">Act. 11.26</note> Chriſtians take their name of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> it is very reaſonable, that wee ſhould bee moſt diligente in learnyng his Doctrine, that wee may knowe what to profeſſe, &amp; moſte circumſpect in obſeruing his imitable woorkes, that we may expreſſe our Religion by our life. So ſhall wee bee<note n="(i)" place="margin">Iam. 1.22.</note> 
               <hi>doers of the worde and not hearers onelie,</hi> ſo ſhall wee <hi>not deceiue our owneſelues.</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:19080:14" rendition="simple:additions"/> And that yee may knowe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> as <hi>Chriſts</hi> Doctrine is to bee learned, ſo his life is to bee imitated, I beſeach you call to minde y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he perſuaded his <hi>Diſciples</hi> to bee<note n="a" place="margin">Mat 11.2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> 
               <hi>meeke,</hi> becauſe <hi>hee was meeke,</hi> and to<note n="b" place="margin">Ioh. 13.34, &amp; 15.12.</note> 
               <hi>loue one an other,</hi> becauſe <hi>he had loued them</hi> ſaying:<note n="c" place="margin">Mat. 11.29</note> 
               <hi>learne of mee,</hi> that <hi>I Am meeke and lowly in hearte:</hi> and<note n="d" place="margin">Ioh. 13.14 &amp; 15.12.</note> 
               <hi>loue ye one an other, as I haue loued you.</hi> If we compare age with age &amp; faulte with faulte, we finde, that ignorance and ſuperſtition were the blottes of the age paſt, and that the blemiſhes of our age are care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſneſſe, as well in learning <hi>Gods</hi> will in his worde, as in expreſſing the ſame in our life, in ſome: and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſimulation counterfeityng loue with men and zeale to <hi>God,</hi> in others. How farre theſe men are from the right imitation of <hi>Chriſt</hi>
               <note n="e" place="margin">Ioh. 2.17.</note> 
               <hi>which was eaten vp with the zeale of <hi>Gods</hi> houſe,</hi> and<note n="f" place="margin">1. Pet. 2.22.</note> in <hi>whoſe mouth was found no guile, <hi>God</hi>
               </hi>
               <note n="g" place="margin">Act. 1.24.</note> 
               <hi>which knoweth the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretes of the hearte,</hi> doth knowe, and their conſciences, wherein they are giftie, doe beare them witneſſe. Hath
<pb facs="tcp:19080:14" rendition="simple:additions"/> 
               <hi>God</hi> light vp the<note n="a" place="margin">Pſal. 119.105</note> candle of his worde in our age, and doe wee con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temne the benifite of the light; <q>Hath <hi>God</hi> deliuered vs in theſe daies many<note n="b" place="margin">Mat 25.15</note> talentes, &amp; do wee deliuer him none backe with increaſe? what then muſt we looke for?</q> Suerly,<note n="c" place="margin">Mat 21.43.</note> 
               <hi>to haue his worde taken from vs, and to bee giuen to a nation, that will bring forth the fruites thereof:</hi> and<note n="d" place="margin">26.25.</note> 
               <hi>to be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priued of the talentes, which ſhall bee de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuered to good and faithfull ſeruantes,</hi> which will vſe them with increaſe. O then my brethren, let vs ſtriue to attaine that happineſſe <hi>which <hi>Chriſt</hi>
               </hi> pronounceth to ſtande<note n="e" place="margin">Luc. 11.28.</note> 
               <hi>in hearing the worde of <hi>God</hi> and keeping it.</hi> And hetherto how <hi>God</hi> may bee imitated by vs in his Sonne <hi>Chriſt Ieſus</hi> our <hi>Lorde.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note n="*" place="margin">3. in his Saints.</note>Thirdelie <hi>God</hi> ſetteth forth him-ſelfe to bee imitated of vs<note n="f" place="margin">1. Cor. 4, 16 1. Theſ. 1.6</note> in his <hi>Sainctes.</hi> And hereby our heauenly <hi>Father</hi> ſetteth forth vnto our vewe, as in a glaſſe, the power of the opera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of his <hi>holie ſpirite</hi> in<note place="margin">2. Cor. 4.7</note> ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then veſſels. For when wee conſider,
<pb facs="tcp:19080:15" rendition="simple:additions"/> that the faithfull ſeruants of the <hi>Lord,</hi> whoſe prayſe is in the worde of <hi>God,</hi> were<note n="(a)" place="margin">Iam. 5.17.</note> 
               <hi>ſubiect to the ſame infir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities, that wee are,</hi> and yet neuerthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe, ſhone in ſundrie virtues, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by wee my learne, that wee,<note n="(b)" place="margin">Io. 15.5.</note> 
               <hi>which of our ſelues can do nothing,</hi> yet <hi>abidyng in <hi>Chriſt</hi>
               </hi> by faith, and <hi>Chriſt <hi>abidyng in vs</hi>
               </hi> by his <hi>Spirite, <hi>may bring forth much fruite.</hi>
               </hi> So the miſtruſt, which might riſe thorowe our owne weake<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe in ourſelues, is remoued by the conſideration of the mightie operati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of <hi>Gods Spirite</hi> in others. For we muſt not thinke<note n="(c)" place="margin">Deut 10.17, 2. Chro. 19.17. Iob. 34.19. Act. 10.34. Rom. 2.11. Gal. 2.6. Ephe. 6.9. Col. 3.21. 1. Pet. 1.17.</note> that <hi>God <hi>is an ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepter of perſons,</hi>
               </hi>
               <note n="(d)" place="margin">Act. 10.35. The ſaints virtues to be imitated.</note> 
               <hi>but that in euerie na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, he that feareth him, and woorketh righteouſnes, is accepted with him.</hi> we muſt therfore diligentlie ſearch forth the vertues of the ſeruaunts of <hi>God,</hi> that we imitating their good workes, may imitate <hi>God,</hi> which ſetteth him ſelfe forth in them by vs to bee imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tated. So then we muſt learne righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe, of<note n="(e)" place="margin">Gen. 6.9. &amp; 7.2.</note> righteous <hi>Noe:</hi> faith, of<note n="(f)" place="margin">15.6. rom. 4.3. Gal. 3.6. Ia. 2.23.</note> faithfull <hi>Abraham:</hi> chaſtitie, of<note n="(g)" place="margin">Gen. 39.8.</note> chaſte <hi>Ioſeph:</hi> meekeneſſe of
<pb facs="tcp:19080:15" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <note n="(a)" place="margin">Num. 12, 13.</note> meeke, Moſes: we muſt learne <hi>zeal</hi> of<note n="(b)" place="margin">25.7. &amp; 8.</note> zealous <hi>Phines: <hi>courrage,</hi>
               </hi> of<note n="(c)" place="margin">14.6.7.8.9.</note> courrageous <hi>Ioſua: <hi>vncorrupteneſſe,</hi>
               </hi> of<note n="(d)" place="margin">1. Sam. 12.5.</note> vncorrupte <hi>Samuell.</hi> Wee muſt learne <hi>valianteneſſe</hi> of<note n="(e)" place="margin">17.45.46.47.</note> valiante <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid: <hi>wiſdome,</hi>
               </hi> of<note n="(f)" place="margin">1. King. 3 12.</note> wiſe <hi>Salomon: <hi>pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience</hi>
               </hi> of,<note n="(g)" place="margin">Iob. 1.21. Iam. 5.11.</note> patience <hi>Iob.</hi> I paſſe ouer many rare virtues, which appeared in diuers of <hi>Gods</hi> ſeruantes, mencioned both in the newe Teſtament and in the olde, all which are examples vnto vs, that wee followyng them may be founde<note n="(h)" place="margin">Epheſ. 5.1</note> 
               <hi>followers of <hi>God,</hi> as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commeth deare children.</hi> Let vs there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, brethren, diligently reade the word of <hi>God,</hi> that there finding the godly life of the <hi>Saints</hi> deſcribed, wee may vſe it as a paterne of <hi>Chriſtian</hi> imitation. Neither let vs miſtruſt the merciful aſſiſtance of <hi>Gods holy ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit,</hi>
               <note n="(i)" place="margin">Pſal. 145.18.</note> 
               <hi>which is neare vnto all, that call vpon him truly in faith</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note n="*" place="margin">The Sain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctes muſt be followed with a cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in two pointes.</note>But becauſe<note n="(k)" place="margin">Ia. 3.2.</note> the <hi>Sainctes</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> haue alwaies had their im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfections and blemiſhes, (Such is the frayleneſſe of <hi>mans</hi> nature.) they are not ſo perfect paternes, that wee
<pb facs="tcp:19080:16" rendition="simple:additions"/> may without exception imitate them. Therefore <hi>Paule</hi> addeth this <hi>Caution:</hi>
               <note n="a" place="margin">1. Cor. 11.1.</note> 
               <hi>Euen as I am of Chriſt</hi> teachyng vs thereby, that the <hi>Sainctes</hi> are ſo farre forth to bee followed, as they followe <hi>Chriſt</hi> and no further, neither in <hi>life,</hi> nor in <hi>doctrine.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note n="*" place="margin">1 in life.</note>So then <hi>Noes</hi>
               <note n="b" place="margin">Gen. 9.21.</note> 
               <hi>drunkenneſſe: the <hi>Patriarches</hi>
               </hi>
               <note n="c" place="margin">Gen. 4.19.16.3.29.23.</note> 
               <hi>polygamie: <hi>Ioſephs</hi>
               </hi>
               <note n="d" place="margin">44, 5.</note> 
               <hi>diſſimulation,</hi> is no warrante, that wee may be <hi>dronke,</hi> or <hi>at one time haue manie wiues,</hi> or <hi>diſſemble.</hi> This cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion obſerued, wee may not imitate <hi>Moſes</hi>
               <note n="e" place="margin">Num. 20.11.</note> 
               <hi>miſtruſt</hi> of <hi>God:</hi> nor <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uids</hi>
               <note n="f" place="margin">2 Sam. 11.4.12.9.</note> 
               <hi>adulterie</hi> and <hi>murther:</hi> nor <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naſſes</hi>
               <note n="g" place="margin">2. Chro. 33.2.</note> 
               <hi>idolatrye.</hi> So farre muſt wee bee from imitatyng the <hi>faults</hi> of the <hi>Seruants</hi> of <hi>God</hi> that wee maye not with<note n="h" place="margin">Mat. 26.70 Mar. 14.68. Lu. 22.57. Io. 18, 17, &amp; 27,</note> 
               <hi>Peter <hi>denie</hi> Chriſt:</hi> nor with<note n="i" place="margin">20, 25,</note> 
               <hi>Thomas <hi>doubte of his reſurrection:</hi>
               </hi> nor with<note n="k" place="margin">Act, 15, 39,</note> 
               <hi>Paule</hi> and <hi>Barnabas <hi>fall out among our-ſelues.</hi>
               </hi> And yet theſe, with many like, bee <hi>examples</hi> of the <hi>Fathers,</hi> not of the reprobate, but of the elect, not to bee imitated,<note n="l" place="margin">Gal, 5, 22,</note> as the <hi>fruites of the Spirite,</hi> but to be auoyded,<note n="m" place="margin">19,</note> as the <hi>woorkes of the fleſhe.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:19080:16" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <note n="*" place="margin">2. in Doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine.</note>And as this limitation: <hi>So as the godlie followe <hi>Chriſt,</hi>
               </hi> is to bee obſerued in <hi>maners,</hi> ſo is it in <hi>doctrine.</hi> But the Doctrine, which <hi>Chriſt</hi> taught, was ſuch, as hee confirmed by the writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten worde of <hi>God,</hi> whereby<note n="a" place="margin">Mat, 4, 4, 7.10. Lu, 4, 4, 8, 8, 2 1,</note> hee confounded <hi>Satan,</hi>
               <note n="b" place="margin">18, 21,</note> confirmed his callyng,<note n="c" place="margin">Io, 10, 34,</note> confuted his aduerſaries,<note n="d" place="margin">Luc, 24, 27</note> inſtructed his <hi>Diſciples.</hi> And if wee diligently reade his Sermones, and Epiſtles of the <hi>Apoſtles,</hi> recorded in the booke of the Newe Teſtament, we ſhall finde, that what they taught,<note n="e" place="margin">Rom, 4, 6</note> they confirmed by the holie Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures. For they knewe,<note n="f" place="margin">Io, 5, 39,</note> that <hi>in the Scriptures is eternall life, and that they are they which teſtifie of <hi>Chriſt.</hi>
               </hi> They knewe<note n="g" place="margin">2, Tim, 3, 15,</note> that <hi>the holie Scriptures are able to make men wiſe vnto ſaluation through the faith which is in Chriſt Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus.</hi> They knewe that<note n="h" place="margin">16,</note> 
               <hi>the whole Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture is giuen by inspiration of <hi>God,</hi> and is profitable to teach, to conuince, to cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect, and to inſtruct in righteouſneſſe:</hi>
               <note n="i" place="margin">17,</note> 
               <hi>That the man of <hi>God</hi> may bee abſolute, being made perfect vnto all good workes.</hi> They knewe,<note n="k" place="margin">2, Pet, 1, 20</note> 
               <hi>that no prophecie of the
<pb facs="tcp:19080:17" rendition="simple:additions"/> Scripture is of anie priuate interpretati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on:</hi>
               <note n="(a)" place="margin">21.</note> 
               <hi>and that the prophecie came not in olde time by the will of man: but that ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie men of <hi>god</hi> ſpake, as they were mooued by the holy <hi>ghoſt.</hi>
               </hi> And if this rule: <hi>No further to followe Men, then they followe <hi>Chriſt,</hi>
               </hi> had bine pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſely followed, from the time of the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> vntill our age, <hi>Poperie</hi> had neuer bene ſo vniuerſally receiued in <hi>Chriſtendome,</hi> as, to the loſſe of many ſoules, it hath. For what is <hi>Popery,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Poperie diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cribed.</note> but an hypocriticall Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, brought in by the doctryne of <hi>Men,</hi> with-out the warrant of the worde of <hi>god?</hi> And this much con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cernyng the imitation of <hi>god</hi> in his <hi>Sainctes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note n="*" place="margin">2. God is to bee imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tated of vs, becauſe wee are his deare children.</note>Now it followeth to ſhew the cauſe, (which is the ſecond principal point) why <hi>God</hi> wil, that we immitate him. <hi>Paule</hi> yeeldeth the cauſe heereof ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding<note n="(b)" place="margin">Eph. 5.1.</note> 
               <hi>As deare childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</hi> And in theſe wordes the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> vſeth a moſt ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hement perſuaſion, whether wee way them by naturall reaſon, or in them call to minde the great benefite
<pb facs="tcp:19080:17" rendition="simple:additions"/> which <hi>god</hi> hath beſtowed vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vs. For it ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deth with naturall reaſon, that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> naturall childe imitate y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> naturall fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, in expreſſing, not his vices, but his vertues, that he may be as well y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mirror of his good maners, as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> glaſſe of his co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tenau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce. Ought we not then, which are<note n="a" place="margin">Ioh. 1.12.</note> the ſpirituall children of <hi>god</hi>
               <note n="b" place="margin">Heb. 12.9.</note> the <hi>Father of ſpirites,</hi> to folow him in all things, wherein he hath ſet forth himſelfe, as a paterne to bee fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed, that in our manners we may reſemble him, by bringing forth the fruites of the ſpirite, whereof anone we will ſpeake? And leaſt we ſhould thinke, that hee requireth impoſſible thinges at our hands, (Behold his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therly dealing w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> vs) hee requireth no workes of vs, but ſuch as himſelf, his ſonne, and his ſaints haue done before vs for our example. Now, if the reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braunce of benefites receiued may ſtirre vs vp to duetifulneſſe, <hi>Paule</hi> would haue vs to knowe, that ſince <hi>god</hi> hath vouchſafed to make<note n="c" place="margin">Ioh. 1.12,</note> vs by grace his beloued <hi>children,</hi> whiche<note n="d" place="margin">Ephe. 2.3</note> 
               <hi>by nature</hi> were the <hi>children of wrath,</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:19080:18" rendition="simple:additions"/> our duetie is with all readyneſſe to i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitate him our louyng <hi>Father,</hi>
               <note n="a" place="margin">5.1.</note> 
               <hi>as becommeth deare children.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Two thinges inſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuated in the Greeke wordes.</note>But for ſo much as the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> by vſing choſen woordes in the <hi>greeke</hi> tongue, wherein hee wrote this Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle,<note n="b" place="margin">Ephe. 5.1</note> 
               <hi>Os tecna agapeta,</hi> hath inſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuated, both the meane, whereby we become the <hi>children</hi> of <hi>god,</hi> and the <hi>fruite</hi> thereof, I will briefly ſpeake of thoſe two pointes, and ſo conclud this part.</p>
            <p>
               <note n="*" place="margin">1. The mean wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by we are made Gods children, is a ſpirituall birth.</note>The meane whereby we become <hi>gods <hi>children</hi>
               </hi> is<note n="c" place="margin">Ioh. 1.13.</note> a <hi>byrth, not of bloud, nor of the will of the fleſh, nor of the will of man, but of <hi>god.</hi>
               </hi> This <hi>birth <hi>Chriſt</hi>
               </hi> calleth<note n="d" place="margin">3.3. &amp; 5.</note> a <hi>new birth,</hi> which is wrought by <hi>gods holy ſpirite,</hi>
               <note n="e" place="margin">Heb. 9.14.</note> 
               <hi>which clenſeth our conſciences from dead workes.</hi>
               <note n="f" place="margin">Mat. 3.11.</note> 
               <hi>and inflameth our hartes with the loue of the truth.</hi> And that we may know that this byrth is altogether ſpirituall, <hi>Iames</hi> telleth vs, that<note n="g" place="margin">Iam. 1.18</note> 
               <hi>god <hi>of his own will begate vs with the word of truth:</hi>
               </hi> And <hi>Peter</hi> teacheth vs, that<note n="h" place="margin">1. Pet. 1.23</note> 
               <hi>we are borne a new, not of mortall ſeede, but of immortall, by the worde of <hi>god,</hi> who li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth
<pb facs="tcp:19080:18" rendition="simple:additions"/> and indureth for euer.</hi> So the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ſince euery thing in this birth is moſt excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent,<note n="a." place="margin">Iam. 1.18.</note> the <hi>father, God:</hi>
               <note n="b" place="margin">1. Pet. 1.23</note> the <hi>ſeede,</hi> his <hi>word:</hi>
               <note n="c" place="margin">Ioh. 3.5. &amp; 8.</note> the <hi>worker,</hi> his <hi>ſpirite:</hi>
               <note n="d" place="margin">1.12.</note> 
               <hi>the fruite,</hi> his <hi>children,</hi> the due remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of this gracious meanes, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by we receiue this priuilege to bee<note n="e" place="margin">1.12,</note> the <hi>ſonnes</hi> of <hi>god,</hi> ought to moue vs ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectually to bee<note n="f" place="margin">Ephe. 5.1,</note> 
               <hi>folowers of <hi>god</hi>
               </hi> our <hi>Father, <hi>as beſeemeth deare children.</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note n="*" place="margin">2 The fruit of this ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall birth, is our fauoure with God.</note>The fruite and commoditie, which inſueth vnto vs, by the meanes of this ſpirituall birth, is exceeding great. For thereby we become<note n="g" place="margin">Ephe. 5.1</note> 
               <hi>Agapetoi,</hi> that is, amiable, diligible, acceptable, and pleaſaunt in the ſight of our <hi>god,</hi> in whom hee taketh full delight, as a father in his childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. And this is more then <hi>Agapoumenoi, beloued.</hi> For amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g men, ſome time children are beloued of their parentes affectionately, when their co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dicio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s deſerue no loue at all,<note n="h" place="margin">Gen. 27.6<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </note> as was <hi>Eſau</hi> of <hi>Iſaac.</hi> But by meanes of this new birth, there is cauſe why <hi>god</hi> loueth them, whom he hath ſo re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generate. For thereby we become the members of that holy body, whereof
<pb facs="tcp:19080:19" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <note n="a" place="margin">Ephe. 4.15.</note> 
               <hi>Ieſus Chriſt</hi> is the <hi>head.</hi> And the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it not otherwiſe be, but as<note n="b" place="margin">Luk. 1.35.</note> 
               <hi>Chriſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> the head is holy of it ſelf, ſo muſt tru<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Chriſtians</hi> the members of that head<note n="c" place="margin">Rom. 6.5. 1. Cor. 6.11.</note> participate by grace the holyneſſe o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> their head, wherby they become acce<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ptable &amp; amiable vnto <hi>God.</hi> This mo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ued <hi>Paul</hi> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 
               <hi>Apoſtle</hi> to teach vs, that<note n="d" place="margin">1. Cor. 1.30</note> 
               <hi>we are of <hi>god,</hi> in <hi>Chriſt Ieſus,</hi> Who of <hi>god</hi> is made vnto vs wiſedome, and righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſnes, and ſanctificatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and rede<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ption<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> And as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> whole body of <hi>Aaro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               </hi> became fragra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t by the meanes of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> precious<note n="e" place="margin">Exo. 30.30</note> 
               <hi>ointement,</hi>
               <note n="f" place="margin">Pſal. 133.2.</note> 
               <hi>which distilled from his head to the hemme of his garmentes,</hi> &amp; as his whole body was glorious through his<note n="g" place="margin">Exod. 28.2</note> beautifull attire, ſo is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> whole body of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> (<note n="h" place="margin">1. Cor. 6, 15</note> 
               <hi>whereof we be members</hi>) ſweete in the preſence of <hi>god,</hi> through the ſanctification of his <hi>ſpirite,</hi> &amp; glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious before him, through the righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe of his <hi>ſonne.</hi> For through <hi>Chriſt</hi> we, as<note n="i" place="margin">1. Pet. 2.5</note> 
               <hi>liuely ſtones be made a spirituall houſe, an holy Prieſthode to of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer vp spirituall ſacrifices acceptable to <hi>god</hi> by <hi>Ieſus Chriſt</hi>
               </hi>
               <note n="k" place="margin">9</note> yea, we <hi>are a choſen generation, a royall Prieſthode, an
<pb facs="tcp:19080:19" rendition="simple:additions"/> holy nation, a people ſet at libertie, that we ſhould ſhew forth the vertues of him that hath called vs foorth of darkeneſſe into this merueilous light.</hi> And thus you heare how both <hi>Peter</hi> and <hi>Paul</hi> by the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ue remembraunce of theſe gracious giftes, whiche neceſſarily folow our<note n="a" place="margin">Ephe. 1.5,</note> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> adoption into the children of <hi>god,</hi> through our regeneration<note n="b" place="margin">Ioh. 3.5. &amp; 8</note> wrought by his <hi>ſpirite,</hi> do earneſtly exhorte vs to<note n="c" place="margin">Ephe. 5.1</note> 
               <hi>be folowers of <hi>god,</hi> as</hi> becommeth <hi>deare childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</hi> And this much touching the cauſes, why <hi>god</hi> will that we bee folowers of him.</p>
            <p>
               <note n="*" place="margin">3. God is to by imita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king in loue.</note>Now foloweth the third point in this doctrine of imitation to be obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued: wherein <hi>god</hi> is to be imitated. This doth the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> teach vs, when as hee addeth:<note n="d" place="margin">Ephe, 5.2</note> 
               <hi>And walke in loue:</hi> whereby he ſheweth, that then we fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low <hi>god,</hi> as deare children,<note n="e" place="margin">Ioh. 13.14 15.12.</note> when we loue one an other, as <hi>Chriſt</hi> hath loued vs. And ſurely the<note n="f" place="margin">Mat. 11.30</note> 
               <hi>yocke,</hi> which our heauenly <hi>Father</hi> layeth vppon the neckes of vs his children, <hi>is light<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> and the ſeruice, which he requireth of vs is ſweete, when as all the practiſe
<pb facs="tcp:19080:20" rendition="simple:additions"/> of al our obedience ſtandeth in loue, moſt ſweete affectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of a godly min<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> The <hi>Apoſtle</hi> meanyng to ſtirre vs v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> effectually in this amiable imitatio<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of <hi>god,</hi> vſeth a metaphore drawen fr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> walking in the way, whereby hee de<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cribeth vnto vs that loue, wherein co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſiſteth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> true imitation of <hi>god.</hi> Ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore that the depth of this doctrin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> may be ſounded, it ſhall behoue vs t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> examine euery circu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtance of the way<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> which being knowen vnto vs by expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience, may giue light vnto the mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyng of this ſpeach:<note n="a" place="margin">Ephe. 5.2.</note> 
               <hi>Walke in loue.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Foure thinges are to be obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued in this kinde of walking.</note>Now the circumſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ces in numbe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> are foure: The firſt, <hi>whoſe the way is<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> wherein we muſt walke: The ſecond, <hi>what the marke</hi> of this way is: Th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> third, <hi>of what maner the exerciſe</hi> of thi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> way is: The fourth, <hi>what the ende</hi> o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> this way is.</p>
            <p>
               <note n="*" place="margin">1. The waie where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in wee muſt walk, are the commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dements of God.</note>The way, wherin we muſt walk<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> is the kinges path, the common hig<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> way of all <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> without excep<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>tion, euen the ordinances of the <hi>Lord</hi> which he hath giuen to all his people by them to be obſerued, with all duti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full
<pb facs="tcp:19080:20" rendition="simple:additions"/> reuerence. And therefore the lawe of <hi>God,</hi> the ſecond time publiſhed by <hi>Moſes,</hi> is thus intituled:<note n="a" place="margin">Deut. 1.1</note> theſe be the <hi>words, which Moſes ſpake vnto all Iſraell &amp;c.</hi> Neither did <hi>Moſes</hi> the ſeruaunt of the <hi>Lord</hi> forget, when hee propoſed the Abbridgement of all <hi>Gods</hi> lawes, contained in<note n="b" place="margin">Exod. 20. Deut. 5.1.</note> ten pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eptes,<note n="c" place="margin">7.</note> 
               <hi>to call together all Iſraell, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o exhort all <hi>Iſraell,</hi> to harken to the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinaunces and lawes of the <hi>Lorde,</hi> that they might learne them, obſerue them, and keepe them.</hi> Therefore as <hi>God</hi> is the <hi>Lorde</hi> of al <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> ſo is he to be obeyed of al <hi>Chriſtians.</hi> Nowe, as he hath laid open his high way, (euen his holy lawes) for all his ſubiectes to walke in, ſo let vs all learne, by his holy worde, to walke therein before him, with all integritie.<note n="d" place="margin">Act. 10.34. Rom. 2.11.</note> 
               <hi>God is no accepter of perſons.</hi> Therefore let euery man conſider his callings, and learne, by <hi>Gods</hi> worde, to walke be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Lorde according to his voca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.<note n="e" place="margin">Eſay. 49.23</note> 
               <hi>Princes, <hi>in foſtering, cheriſhing, and gouerning</hi> Gods <hi>church:</hi>
               </hi>
               <note n="f" place="margin">Mat. 23.17 Mat. 12.17. Luk. 20.25. Rom. 13.1. &amp;c. tit. 3.1. 1. Pet. 3.13.</note> 
               <hi>Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iectes <hi>in obeying their Princes:</hi>
               </hi>
               <note n="g" place="margin">Pro. 8.15</note> 
               <hi>No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blemen,
<pb facs="tcp:19080:21" rendition="simple:additions"/> 
                  <hi>in making good lawes:</hi>
               </hi>
               <note n="a" place="margin">Rom. 13.3 &amp; 4.</note> 
               <hi>M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>giſtrates, <hi>in executing iuſtice:</hi>
               </hi>
               <note n="b" place="margin">2. Tim, 2.15,</note> 
               <hi>Min<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ſters, <hi>in cutting aright vnto</hi> gods <hi>fam<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>lie, the bread of life,</hi>
               </hi>
               <note n="c" place="margin">Iam. 1.19.</note> 
               <hi>which is the wor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of truth, as beco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth</hi>
               <note n="d" place="margin">1. Cor. 4.1. &amp; 2</note> 
               <hi>faithful ſtewar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> in the <hi>Lordes</hi> houſe:</hi>
               <note n="e" place="margin">Ephe. 5.25 Col. 3.19, 1. Pet. 3, 7.</note> 
               <hi>Huſbandes <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>louing their</hi> VViues,</hi>
               <note n="f" place="margin">Ephe. 5.22. Col. 3 18, Tit. 2, 5. 1. Pet. 3.1</note> 
               <hi>Wiues, <hi>in ſu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>mitting themſelues vnto their huſband</hi>
               </hi>
               <note n="g" place="margin">Ephe. 6, 4, Col. 3.21</note> 
               <hi>Parentes, <hi>in nurturing their childre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi>
               </hi>
               <note n="h" place="margin">Ephe. 6.1,</note> 
               <hi>Children, <hi>in obeying their parentes <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> the</hi> Lorde:</hi>
               <note n="i" place="margin">Epheſ. 6.1,</note> 
               <hi>Maiſters, <hi>in cheriſhin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> christianly their ſeruantes:</hi>
               </hi>
               <note n="k" place="margin">Col. 3.22. Tit. 2.9,</note> 
               <hi>Seruants <hi>in ſeruing faythfully their maisters:</hi>
               </hi> An<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> to conclude<note n="l" place="margin">Ephe. 4<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 1,</note> euery one of vs: <hi>to walk<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> worthie of the vocation, whereunto w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> are called, that we may be</hi>
               <note n="m" place="margin">5.1,</note> 
               <hi>followers o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>God,</hi> as dear children.</hi> For<note n="n" place="margin">Mat. 25.14</note> what tal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>le<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t ſoeuer <hi>god</hi> in mercy hath beſtow<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ed vpon vs, hee hath therefore giuen it vs, (yea though it be but a handi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craft,) to vſe to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> glorie of his name, and to the benefite of his Churche<note n="o" place="margin">Eſa, 30.21</note> 
               <hi>This is the way, let vs walke in it.</hi> And now to the ſecond circu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtance of this waye of the <hi>Lorde</hi> wherein wee muſt walke.</p>
            <p>
               <note n="*" place="margin">2. The marke of the way of true Chriſtians is Loue,</note>
               <hi>The marke of the waye is Loue.</hi> For
<pb facs="tcp:19080:21" rendition="simple:additions"/> ſo ſpeaketh the <hi>Apoſtle</hi>
               <note n="a" place="margin">Ephe, 5, 2</note> 
               <hi>Walke in loue.</hi> Conſider, dearely beloued, the great care, whiche our heauenly <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther</hi> taketh for vs his children, who: leaſt we ſhuld wander out of the way, wherein wee ought to walke, giueth vs a marke to know our way by, euen <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oue. This loue is that<note n="b." place="margin">Rom. 13.8</note> 
               <hi>onely debt,</hi> which <hi>god</hi> alloweth vs <hi>to owe one vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to an other.</hi> And the payment of thys debt is ſo acceptable, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Paul</hi> pronoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceth:<note n="c" place="margin">Rom, 13, 8</note> 
               <hi>Whoſoeuer loueth an other,</hi> as he ought, <hi>hath fulfilled the lawe</hi> of <hi>god.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Loue dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, 1. of God 2, of our neighbour,</note>Now, <hi>this loue,</hi> which is the mark of our way, <hi>is double:</hi> Firſt <hi>the loue of <hi>god,</hi>
               </hi> then <hi>the loue of our <hi>neighbour.</hi>
               </hi> Of this abridgement of al our obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence required by <hi>gods</hi> lawes, <hi>chriſt</hi> himſelfe is the collector, who calleth<note n="d" place="margin">Mat. 22, 38 Mar, 12, 30,</note> 
               <hi>the loue of <hi>God,</hi> the firſt and great commaundement: and</hi>
               <note n="e" place="margin">Mat, 22, 39 Mar, 12, 31,</note> 
               <hi>the loue of our</hi> Neighbour, the ſecond, and like vnto the firſt. And that wee might learne, to walke in the waye of the Lorde, within theſe boundes, our <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour chriſt</hi> teacheth vs, that oure
<pb facs="tcp:19080:22" rendition="simple:additions"/> loue muſt bee vnfeyned in either re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect. For <hi>god</hi> requireth, that<note n="a" place="margin">Deut. 6.5. Luk. 10.27</note> wee loue him, with all our heart, and with al our ſoule, and with al our ſtrength, and with all our thought:<note n="b" place="margin">Leu. 19.18 Luk. 10.27.</note> and that we loue our Neighbour, as wee loue our ſelfe. And thus ye ſee, what ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of loue it is, which is the marke of our ſpirituall high-way, altogether ſincere, and no whit hipocriticall.</p>
            <p>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Two thinges in loue to bee obſerued.</note>But will you yet learne more ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>actly how to diſcerne the marke, that thereby you may know the way? Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue then two thinges: <hi>what loue doth not, and what it doth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note n="*" place="margin">1. VVhat loue doth not</note>
               <hi>What loue doth not, <hi>Paule</hi>
               </hi> layeth downe plainly, when as hee ſayth:<note n="c" place="margin">1. Cor. 13.4</note> 
               <hi>Loue enuieth not, loue boaſteth not it ſelfe, loue is not puffed vp. Loue doth none vncomely thinges:</hi>
               <note place="margin">5</note> 
               <hi>loue ſeeketh not her owne thinges: loue is not prouoked to anger:</hi>
               <note place="margin">6</note> 
               <hi>loue thinketh none euill: loue reioyceth not in iniquitie:</hi>
               <note place="margin">8</note> 
               <hi>loue neuer falleth away.</hi> And doe wee ſuch thinges, and yet we are in the way? Surely then <hi>Paule</hi> was farre out of the way, which
<pb facs="tcp:19080:22" rendition="simple:additions"/> thus deſcribed the marke of the waye by the negatiues. Well my brethren, let vs not deceiue our ſelues, for <hi>god</hi> neither mocketh,<note n="a" place="margin">Gal. 6.7.</note> 
               <hi>nor is mocked.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note n="*" place="margin">2. VVhat loue doth.</note>But <hi>what doth loue,</hi> that we may know the work of our way by the af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmatiues alſo? Heare <hi>Paule</hi> ſpeake:<note n="b" place="margin">1. Cor. 13.</note> 
               <note place="margin">4.</note> 
               <hi>Loue ſuffereth long: loue is boun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifull: loue reioyceth in the trueth:</hi>
               <note place="margin">6</note> 
               <hi>Loue beleueth all thinges:</hi>
               <note place="margin">7</note> 
               <hi>loue in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dureth all thinges.</hi> And can wee be in the way, except we do theſe things? No vndoubtedly: For this is the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubted marke of the waye. O then, deare, brethren, let vs bring forth the fruites of <hi>Loue,</hi> that it may appeare, we walke in <hi>loue.</hi> So ſhall wee be bleſſed, being<note n="c" place="margin">Iam. 1.22.</note> 
               <hi>not onely hearers of the word, but doers therof:</hi> So ſhall we <hi>not deceiue our owne ſelues.</hi> Wee delight greatly to talke of Loue, <hi>God</hi> graunt we may learne to walk in Loue. And this muche of the marke of the waye, wherein all true <hi>Chriſtians</hi> ought to walke.</p>
            <p>
               <note n="*" place="margin">3. The manner of wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king in this way, muſt be a continuall exerciſe of godlyneſſe.</note>Now wee come to the third cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtance of this waye of righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe,
<pb facs="tcp:19080:23" rendition="simple:additions"/> which is the path for the childr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of <hi>God</hi> vpon earth to walke in. Fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> it is not inough to walke in this way (whereof I firſt ſpake) and by the marke to know the way; (which point was laſtly handled) but we muſt alſo learne <hi>the maner of walking,</hi> whereby our iournieng is brought to an happy end. And this is the maner of our ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall walking, that we walke con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually in the Loue of <hi>God,</hi> and our <hi>Neighbour</hi>
               <note n="a" place="margin">Gen, 17, 7,</note> The league, whiche <hi>God</hi> made with <hi>Abraham</hi> and hys ſeed,<note n="b" place="margin">Gal, 3, 9,</note> (which are we if we be indued with the fayth of <hi>Abraham</hi>) was not momentary, but perpetuall.<note n="c" place="margin">Gen, 17, 1, 7,</note> And this is the league, that the almighty wil be our God, in perfourming hys good promiſes, and deliuering vs fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> euils, not for an houre, or a day, or a yeare, but for euer: and that we walk before him, and be perfect, not for an houre, or a daye, or a yeare, but<note n="d" place="margin">Luc, 1.74, &amp; 74,</note> all our liues long. For as the protection of God, to vs his people, is continual ſo is it meet, that our obedience, vnto him our <hi>God</hi> ſhuld be continual alſo.
<pb facs="tcp:19080:23" rendition="simple:additions"/> and this continuall exerciſe of godly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eſſe, did <hi>god</hi> inioyne <hi>Abraham,</hi> and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s in <hi>Abraham,</hi> when as at the coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t making he ſaid vnto him:<note n="a" place="margin">Gen, 17, 1,</note> 
               <hi>Hith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aller lephanai,</hi> which by the proprietie of the <hi>Hebrue</hi> verbe in the coniuga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ion <hi>Hithpael,</hi> wherein it is vſed, doth ſignifie a continuall walkyng before the <hi>Lord</hi> in perfect obedie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce vnto his lawes. And leaſt we ſhould want a co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable example to lead vs on in this co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinuall exerciſe of dutifull obedie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce to our <hi>God,</hi>
               <note n="b" place="margin">Gen, 5, 22 &amp; 24, In Hebrue Ijthallec, in Engliſh, Hee walked con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually.</note> 
               <hi>Enoch</hi> is reported <hi>to haue walked continually with the <hi>Lord</hi>
               </hi> all his life lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g,<note n="c" place="margin">Gen, 5, 23</note> euen <hi>365</hi> yeares, in that hee folowed not the naughtineſſe of his age, neither was ſteined with the corrupt worſhipping of <hi>god</hi> with other, but worſhipped him <hi>continually,</hi> according to his commaundementes, in fayth, integritie of hart, and inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cencie of life, <hi>whom</hi> the <hi>Lord,</hi> of his free fauour,<note n="d" place="margin">Gen, 5, 24 Heb, 11, 5,</note> 
               <hi>did tranſlate that hee ſhould not ſee death.</hi> Oh happy man ſo long in ſeruice with ſo good a <hi>Lord:</hi> Oh bleſſed <hi>god,</hi> acceptyng ſo mercy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully in the <hi>Meſsias</hi> the obedience of
<pb facs="tcp:19080:24" rendition="simple:additions"/> his ſeruaunt! And ſhall we leaue ſo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſweete an example vnimitated? O<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſhall we neglect ſo great graces o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> perpetually bliſſe purpoſed vnto vs in ſo certaine an example? <hi>god</hi> forbid<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> For there can be nothing in this lyfe more ſweete, then <hi>continually</hi> to ſerue the <hi>Lorde,</hi> neither can there bee any thyng after this life more excellent, then <hi>continually</hi> to liue with the <hi>Lord.</hi> And both theſe thynges are propoſed vnto vs in this excellent example. Oh let vs then, my brethren, not thinke it tedious to walke continually in loue. Now let vs conſider on the contrary part, how perilous a thing it is, not to walke <hi>continually</hi> in due obedience, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the <hi>Lord,</hi> whiche the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendeth here, when as he exhorteth vs<note n="a" place="margin">Ephe. 5.12.</note> 
               <hi>to walke in loue.</hi> Herein the example of the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> behauiour in their co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myng forth of <hi>Egypt</hi> may ſtand vs in good ſteede. For <hi>god</hi>
               <note n="b" place="margin">Num. 14.22.23.29.30</note> denied en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traunce into the land of promiſe,<note n="c" place="margin">Exod, 3.8.17.13.5.32.3 Deut. 6.3.11.9</note> whiche flowed with milke and honie, vnto all thoſe <hi>Iſraelites,</hi> which in their hartes turned backe in the wildernes
<pb facs="tcp:19080:24" rendition="simple:additions"/> to <hi>Egypt,</hi>
               <note n="a" place="margin">Num. 14.24.30.</note> and graunted the ſame <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nely vnto <hi>Ioſuah</hi> and <hi>Caleb</hi> his ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>auntes, whiche walked <hi>continually</hi> i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the way, with chearefull myndes, in full aſſuraunce of the performance of <hi>gods</hi> promiſſes. But beſides the truth of the hiſtorie,<note n="b" place="margin">Pſal. 95.11. Heb. 4.8.9.</note> the temporall reſt in the land, of promiſe, is a figure of the euerlaſtyng reſt in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> kingdome of heauen. If therefore <hi>God</hi> thus pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed the neglecting of his temporal gifts, how much more wil he be reuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged vpon the contemners of the ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual graces? We may not then looke, my brethren, to enter into the kyng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of <hi>God,</hi> except we walke on <hi>co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually</hi> in loue, which is the way, that leadeth into euerlaſting life. We know litle in the ſpirituall rynnyng, if we know not,<note n="c" place="margin">2. Tim. 2 9</note> that <hi>they onely re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue the garland, which runne to the end of the race.</hi> Wee are ignorau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t in the ſpirituall huſbandry, if we bee igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raunt,<note n="d" place="margin">Luc. 9.26.</note> that <hi>hee, whiche putteth his hand to the plow, and looketh backe, is not worthy of the kingdome of <hi>God.</hi>
               </hi> Wee wotte not to whome bleſſedneſſe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longeth,
<pb facs="tcp:19080:25" rendition="simple:additions"/> if we wot not, that it belon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth to them onely,<note n="a" place="margin">Mat, 10, 22 24, 13, Mar, 12, 13,</note> whiche perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer vnto the ende, So then it follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, that nothing is more required in the children of God, than a conti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>all exerciſe in all godlineſſe. How ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> we be ſtarres in the Lords firmamen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <note n="b" place="margin">Dan, 12, 3. Mat, r 3, 43,</note> 
               <hi>except we ſhine continually in holines<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> Or ſouldiers in his campe,<note n="c" place="margin">Mat. 24, 42 25, 13, 26, 41, Mar. 13, 33,</note> except <hi>we ſtand continually vpon our watch</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the ſpirituall aduerſary? Or trees of his garden of <hi>Eden,</hi>
               <note n="d" place="margin">Pſal, 1, 3,</note> except <hi>we grow continually</hi> by the vertue of the ſappe of his ſpirite; And can wee be his paſſengers vnto the heauenly Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem,<note n="e" place="margin">Mic, 2.10, Heb, 13, 14,</note> except <hi>we walke on continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally</hi> in the loue of <hi>god,</hi> &amp; of our neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour? wherefore (as the author of the Epiſtle to the <hi>Hebrues</hi> exhorteth vs)<note n="f" place="margin">12, 1,</note> 
               <hi>Let vs runne with patience the race that is ſet before vs. Let vs lift vp our handes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">12,</note> 
               <hi>which hang downe, and our weake knees, and make ſtraight ſteppes to our feete,</hi>
               <note place="margin">13,</note> 
               <hi>leaſt that which is halting, be tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned out of the way, but let it rather bee healed. Yea,</hi>
               <note n="g" place="margin">Exo. 12.11</note> 
               <hi>let vs make haſt to the promiſed land, with our loynes girte, our
<pb facs="tcp:19080:25" rendition="simple:additions"/> ſhoes on our feete, and ſtaues in our ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds,</hi> that we ſtay not in the way, whiche leadeth from this worldly <hi>Egypt,</hi> vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the heauenly promiſed land. And this much concerning the manner of walking in the way, whiche leadeth into euerlaſting life.</p>
            <p>
               <note n="*" place="margin">4. The end of the way is euerlaſting life.</note>Now remaineth, that we ſhew you the <hi>ende</hi> of the way, which in order is the fourth circumſtance. The ende of the way, wherein the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth vs to walke, is <hi>euerlaſting life.</hi> Neither is it without cauſe, that I propoſe vnto you the ende of our wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king. For the end of all actions, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing firſt in intention, and laſt in exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution, is by experience found to be of that force, that it draweth vs on, (al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though it ſtand with our perill) to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pliſh y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we intend, in hope to atchiue y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> end, in our minds firſt propoſed. And therfore <hi>Chriſt</hi> our <hi>Sauiour,</hi> to incou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage vs<note n="a" place="margin">Mat. 7.14</note> 
               <hi>to enter in at the ſtraite gate, &amp; to walk in the narrow way,</hi> of due obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience vnto <hi>God,</hi> propoſeth the ende, which is <hi>life,</hi> And on the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trary part, to deterre vs<note n="b" place="margin">Mat. 7.13.</note> from <hi>entryng through
<pb facs="tcp:19080:26" rendition="simple:additions"/> the wide gate, and walking in the broa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> way</hi> of licentiouſneſſe, he propoſeth al<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſo the end, which is <hi>Deſtruction.</hi> And what can bee more comfortable the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> life, and the ſame to bee inioyed eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally in the kingdome of heauen? O<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> what can bee more fearefull, then de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtruction, and the ſame to be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinued for euer in hell? Let vs then cheare<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fully walke on in the way of obedie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce ſo ſhall we receiue the promiſed re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward. But that we may with more courage runne our race, in hope to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine the crowne, let vs take a vewe of euerlaſting life, with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> eies of our mynds, as in <hi>gods</hi> word it is diuerſly deſcribed.<note n="*" place="margin">1. Euerlaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting life compared to the land of Canaan.</note> 
               <hi>god</hi> in old time gaue vnto the auncie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t <hi>Iſraelites</hi> the land of Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naan, a land for the fruitefulnes ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, ſayd<note n="a." place="margin">Exod. 3.8, Num. 13.27</note> to <hi>flowe with milke and hony</hi> that they might, not onely poſſeſſe it, accordyng to his<note n="b" place="margin">Gen. 15.14 &amp;c.</note> promiſe, but alſo by the temporall benefites thereof, to be put in mynde of the ſpirituall bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings in the land of the liuyng: and by their earthly reſt there inioyed after y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> bondage in <hi>Egypt,</hi> to be ſtirred vp w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:19080:26"/> the deſire of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> heauenly reſt to be poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſed by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> people of <hi>god,</hi> after their deliuerance fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the thraldom of <hi>Satan.</hi> Read the fourth to the <hi>Hebrues,</hi> and there ſhall you finde this doctrine wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranted. So is the land of <hi>Canaan</hi> a figure of euerlaſting life. <hi>Chriſt</hi> the wiſedome of our heauenly <hi>Father,</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">2. Euerlaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting life called ſalua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</note> wel knoweth, that this tranſitorie life of ours is ſubiect vnto many calamities, and therefore for our incouragement, he calleth euerlaſting life,<note n="a" place="margin">Mat. 10.22 Mat. 13.13.</note> 
               <hi>Saluation</hi> whereby vndoubtedly he would haue vs to know, that euerlaſting life is that bleſſed ſtate, wherein we ſhall be deliuered from all calamities of the body, all griefes of the mynde, all cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of our nature, from ſinne, from death, from <hi>Sata<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</hi> So ſhall our bodies,<note n="b" place="margin">1. Cor. 15</note> 
               <hi>which now are corruptible,</hi>
               <note place="margin">42</note> 
               <hi>become in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corruptible: which now ar ignominious,</hi>
               <note place="margin">43</note> 
               <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>come glorious: which now are weak,</hi>
               <note place="margin">44</note> 
               <hi>becom ſtro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g: which now are natural,</hi>
               <note place="margin">54</note> 
               <hi>become ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual: which now is mortal,</hi>
               <note place="margin">73</note> become im<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mortal. And this <hi>Saluation,</hi> is that <hi>life euerlaſting,</hi> which <hi>chriſt</hi> hath promiſed to giue to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <note n="c" place="margin">Mat. 10.2, Mar. 13.13</note> 
               <hi>which perſeuere in pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence
<pb facs="tcp:19080:27" rendition="simple:additions"/> vnto the end.</hi> I therfore co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>clude w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the <hi>Apoſtle:</hi>
               <note n="a" place="margin">1. Co. 15.57</note> 
               <hi>Tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>kes be vnto god, which hath giue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vs victory through our Lord Ieſus Chriſt:</hi>
               <note place="margin">58.</note> 
               <hi>Therfore, my beloued brethren, be ye ſtedfaſt, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moueable, aboundaunt alwayes in the worke of the Lord, for as much as ye know, that your labour is not in vayne in the Lord. Chriſt</hi> our <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour,</hi> regarding the groſſenes of our capacitie in heauenly myſteries, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pareth <hi>euerlaſting life</hi> els where, to<note n="b" place="margin">Luc. 22, 29 30.</note> a <hi>kingdome, wherein we ſhall eate and drinke at his table, and ſit on ſeates, and iudge the twelue tribes of <hi>Iſraell.</hi>
               </hi> By theſe earthly and corporall benefites, <hi>Chriſt</hi> ſignifieth heauenly and ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all bleſſinges, aſſuring vs, that, in the world to come, we ſhall haue the frui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the <hi>Lord,</hi> and with him the ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of felicitie. And this is euerla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting life. But know this, that this onely belongeth to them,<note n="c" place="margin">Luc. 22, 28.</note> whiche <hi>continue</hi> with <hi>Chriſt <hi>in his tentations.</hi>
               </hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">3. Euerlaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting life com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pared to a kingdome.</note> To ſet foorth vnto vs the exceedyng glorie of eternall life,<note n="d" place="margin">1, Co. 9.25 2. Tim. 4.8.</note> 
               <hi>Paule,</hi>
               <note n="e" place="margin">Iam. 1.12.</note> 
               <hi>Iames,</hi>
               <note n="f" place="margin">Reue. 2.10</note> and the <hi>Spirite</hi> in the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uelation
<pb facs="tcp:19080:27"/> liken it to a <hi>Crowne,</hi> or <hi>Gar<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>and,</hi> which was wont to be ſet, in ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ourable maner, vppon their heades,<note n="*" place="margin">Euerlaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing life com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pared to a Crowne or Garland.</note> which in making maſteries got the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eſt. But withal hereby they fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warne vs, that except<note n="a" place="margin">2. Tim. 2.5.</note> 
               <hi>wee striue for the maiſterie,</hi> and that <hi>lawfully,</hi> we may <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ot looke to bee crowned.<note n="b" place="margin">1. Cor. 15.54</note> O noble <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ictorie atchieued for vs by <hi>Chriſt,</hi> where <hi>Satan, hell, ſinne, the fleſhe, the world, and all the enimies of our ſaluati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> at once were thoroughly ſubdued, ſo that now he triumpheth ouer them in eternal bliſſe. Let vs therfore fight manfully vnder his ſtandard, that we may bee crowned gloriouſly in his kingdome. But ſince the ende is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies freſh in the eye of the minde,<note n="c" place="margin">1. Cor. 2.9,</note> (as is before ſayd) <hi>Paule</hi> vndoubtedly much meditated vpon the ende of our ſpiritual walking,<note n="*" place="margin">Euerlaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing life com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pared to ioyes not ſeene, not heard, not conceiued.</note> whiche is (as I haue ſhewed) <hi>eternall life.</hi> And yet, his excellent reuelation notwithſtanding as one not able in wordes to deſcribe <hi>euerlasting life,</hi> he leaueth it to the me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditations of our mindes, ſhewing vs, that<note n="c" place="margin">1. Cor. 2.9,</note> 
               <hi>the thinges which God hath pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared
<pb facs="tcp:19080:28"/> for them which loue him, are</hi> ſuche and ſo excelle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, <hi>as the eye hath not ſeene, neither eare hath heard, nor hath come into the heart of man.</hi> And to conclude, we haue a moſte excellent portrature of this eternall life in the <hi>21.</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">6. Euerlaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting life compared to a goodly citie.</note> chapter of the <hi>Reuelation</hi> of <hi>Iohn,</hi> where it is co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pared to a <hi>citie</hi> curiouſly built, gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed with golde and pretious ſtones beautified within and without. In which deſcription, as all thinges are moſt excellent, ſo this is moſt comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table vnto the elect, that, whereas he ſaw no temple, he yealdeth the reaſon:<note n="a" place="margin">Reue. 21 22 23</note> 
               <hi>For, the Lorde God almightie<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and the lambe, are the temple of it.</hi> Adding: <hi>And this city hath no need of the ſun, neither of the moone to ſhine in it: for the glory of God did light it: &amp; the lambe is the light of it.</hi>
               <note place="margin">24</note> 
               <hi>And the people, which are ſaued ſhall walk in the light of it: And the kinges of the earth ſhall bring their glory and their honour vnto it. And the gates of it ſhall not be ſhut by daye:</hi>
               <note place="margin">25</note> 
               <hi>for there ſhall be no night there.</hi>
               <note place="margin">26</note> 
               <hi>And the glory &amp; honor of the
<pb facs="tcp:19080:28" rendition="simple:additions"/> Gentiles ſhall bee brought vnto it.</hi>
               <note place="margin">27</note> 
               <hi>And there ſhall enter into it none vncleane thing, neyther whatſoeuer worketh abhomination or lyes: but they, which are writte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in the lambs booke of life.</hi> O gracious <hi>God,</hi> which in mercie haſt prepared ſo glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious a place for thy ſeruauntes. Thy name be prayſed: Thy name be pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed. But calling to mind our filthines through ſinne, let vs<note n="a" place="margin">Reuel. 7.14</note> 
               <hi>waſhe our robes through faithfull repentance in the bloud of the lamb, that they may become white:</hi> and let vs glorifie Gods name by a godly life, that it may appeare, that we are his children: Otherwiſe wee may not promiſe to our ſelues the fru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ition of that reſt. And this much con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the ende of the way, which is euerlaſting life.</p>
            <p>
               <note n="*" place="margin">4. The loue where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in God muſt be imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tated muſt be vnfained, ſincere and free</note>Now followeth the fourth end &amp; laſt point of the text: How <hi>God</hi> is to be imitated in loue. And this doeth <hi>Paule</hi> laye downe in theſe wordes:<note n="b" place="margin">Ephe. 5.2</note> 
               <hi>Euen as Chriſt hath loued vs, and hath giuen himſelfe for vs <hi>(to be)</hi> an offering, and a ſacrifice of a ſweete
<pb facs="tcp:19080:29" rendition="simple:additions"/> ſmelling ſauour to God.</hi> Heere the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> ſheweth what maner of loue it is, by the practiſing whereof <hi>God</hi> is imitated: Namely, that wee loue <hi>God</hi> and one an other <hi>vnfeynedly, ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerely, and freely without regard of me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rite.</hi> For, not euery ſhew of loue, is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed before <hi>God,</hi> but that loue one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,<note n="*" place="margin">The ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect of our loue double.</note> whiche is agreeable to the nature of that, whiche is loued. Then ſince the obiect of our loue, is double<note n="a" place="margin">Mat 22.37 39 mar. 2.30 31. luc. 10.27,</note> 
               <hi>god</hi> and our <hi>Neighbour,</hi> let vs view their natures apart.<note n="*" place="margin">1. God.</note> 
               <hi>God</hi> is<note n="b" place="margin">Ier. 10.10, Ioh. 17.3. 1. theſ. 1.9.</note> true,<note n="c" place="margin">Leu. 11.44.19.2.1. Pet. 1 16.</note> holy, and the<note n="d" place="margin">Iam. 1.17,</note> fountayne of all goodneſſe. Therefore it is meete, that we ſhould loue him for himſelfe, with an <hi>vnfay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, ſincere, and free loue.</hi> Our <hi>Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour,</hi> (be it, hee be an heathen, yet is he) an excellent creature of <hi>God,</hi>
               <note n="e" place="margin">Gen. 1.26 &amp; 27.5.1.</note> made after his image and ſimilitude.<note n="*" place="margin">2. Our neighbour.</note> Therfore to be beloued for the <hi>Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors</hi> ſake, <hi>vnfaynedly, ſincerely,</hi> &amp; <hi>freely.</hi> How much more ought our loue to be ſuch toward our <hi>Chriſtian neighbor,</hi> conſidering,<note n="f" place="margin">Ephe. 4.24 Col. 3.10.</note> that in him the image of <hi>God,</hi>
               <note n="g" place="margin">Rom. 5.17</note> which was decayed by <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam,</hi> is renued through <hi>chriſt,</hi>
               <note n="h" place="margin">Ioh. 1.12</note> wher<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>by
<pb facs="tcp:19080:29" rendition="simple:additions"/> hee is become thorough grace the <hi>child</hi> of <hi>God,</hi>
               <note n="a" place="margin">Rom. 8.17</note> and the heyre of euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting life. So then it foloweth, that as we ought to loue <hi>god,</hi> with an vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fayned, ſincere and free loue, becauſe he is our <hi>father,</hi> ſo ſhould we loue one an other, vnfaynedly, ſincerely, &amp; free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, becauſe we are his <hi>children.</hi> And this is that manner of loue, whiche if we practiſe<note n="b" place="margin">Ephe. 5.1</note> we become <hi>folowers of God, as deare children.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note n="*" place="margin">The loue, whereby we imitate God two waies deſcribed.</note>But that I digreſſe not from my text, marke, I beſeeche you, my bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, how <hi>Paul</hi> deſcribeth this man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of loue, two wayes in the text: Firſt by a <hi>double example,</hi> the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by <hi>proofe</hi> of the ſecond example.</p>
            <p>
               <note n="*" place="margin">1. By exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple</note>Examples in imitatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> be the play<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt documentes, ſo that they be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect. Now conſider the godly diſcre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of <hi>Paule.</hi> For he heere confirmeth his doctrin by two examples, agaynſt the which none exception can be take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</p>
            <p>
               <note n="*" place="margin">1. Of the father.</note>The firſt example of this vnfay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, ſincere, and free loue, is <hi>God</hi> the <hi>Father,</hi>
               <note n="c" place="margin">Ioh. 3.16.</note> 
               <hi>who ſo loued the worlde, that hee gaue his onely begotten <hi>Sonne,</hi> that
<pb facs="tcp:19080:30" rendition="simple:additions"/> whoſoeuer beleueth in him, ſhould not periſh, but haue euerlaſting life.</hi> If we conſider this gracious dealing of <hi>god</hi> with vs, we ſhall finde it to be a moſt perfect mirrour of his free loue to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardes vs, what ſoeuer herein we way. For if we examine the cauſes of the loue of <hi>God</hi> to vs ward: When in vs, whiche are moſt vniuſt, and moſt vnholy, there was no cauſe, why the moſt iuſt, and moſt holy <hi>God</hi> ſhould loue vs, this loue flowed fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his owne bountie, as from<note n="a" place="margin">Iam. 1.17 1. Ioh. 4.10</note> the fountaine of all goodneſſe. If we ſearch into the <hi>manner</hi> of the loue, wherewith <hi>God</hi> loued vs ſo, and ſo exceedingly, that he gaue to ranſome vs from our ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all bondage,<note n="b" place="margin">1. Pet. 1.18.</note> not <hi>ſiluer, gold, or pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious ſtones,</hi> not onely a creature to ſaue vs creatures,<note n="c" place="margin">Heb. 2.16</note> not an <hi>angell</hi> to deliuer vs <hi>men,</hi>
               <note n="d" place="margin">Ioh. 3.16</note> but his own <hi>ſonne,</hi> yea his onely <hi>Sonne,</hi>
               <note n="e" place="margin">Mat 1.23,</note> 
               <hi>God</hi> to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mayne <hi>God,</hi> and <hi>man,</hi>
               <note n="f" place="margin">Heb. 10.5</note> to be <hi>a ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice,</hi>
               <note n="g" place="margin">Phil. 2.8.</note> by an <hi>ignominious death</hi> to bee offered for vs,<note n="h" place="margin">1. Cor. 6.20.7.23. 1. Pet. 1.19.</note> euen the <hi>price of our redemption.</hi> If we take a vewe of the <hi>ende,</hi> for the which <hi>God</hi> loued vs, we
<pb facs="tcp:19080:30" rendition="simple:additions"/> ſhall perceaue, that it was not to the benefite of himſelfe, or of his <hi>Sonne,</hi>
               <note n="a" place="margin">Rom. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>5,</note> (For <hi>God</hi> in himſelfe, and of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, without his creatures, is abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutely bleſſed) but to our benefite,<note n="b" place="margin">Rom. 4.3.4</note> that wee through him being ſaued,<note n="c" place="margin">Mat. 25.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>4</note> with him might liue bleſſedly for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer. If we ponder, what <hi>God</hi> whiche ſo dearly hath loued vs, requireth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine at our handes: verely nothing,<note n="d" place="margin">Ephe 2.8</note> but that hee giueth vs,<note n="e" place="margin">Rom. 5.1.</note> a liuely fayth to receaue <hi>Chriſt,</hi>
               <note n="f" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Cor. 1, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>0</note> that in him we may receaue all thinges neceſſary for our ſaluation,<note n="g" place="margin">Ephe. 1.4.</note> and that <hi>wee be holy, and without blame before him in loue.</hi> So then ought we to loue, as the <hi>Father</hi> hath loued vs, <hi>vnfaynedly, ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerely, and freely,</hi> that we may be found<note n="h" place="margin">Ephe. 5.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> 
               <hi>followers of <hi>God</hi> as dear childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</hi> But if anie obiect, that the loue of the <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther</hi> is not mentioned in the text, and thereupon inferre, that I digreſſe fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the ſame, I anſwere: It is included in the little word <hi>Cai,</hi> ſo that the ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence may be thus tranſlated:<note n="i" place="margin">1. Ephe. 5.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> 
               <hi>Euen as Chriſt alſo hath loued vs,</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by, by a ſecret ſpeache, the loue of the
<pb facs="tcp:19080:31" rendition="simple:additions"/> 
               <hi>Father</hi> is inſinuated, as in playne tearmes, the loue of the <hi>Sonne</hi> is pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed.</p>
            <p>
               <note n="*" place="margin">2. Of the ſone</note>The ſecond example of this <hi>vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fayned, ſincere,</hi> and <hi>free</hi> loue, is <hi>God</hi> the <hi>Sonne,</hi>
               <note n="a" place="margin">Ioh. 10.11,</note> who as <hi>a good ſhepheard gaue his life for vs his ſheepe:</hi>
               <note n="b" place="margin">Rom. 5.6.</note> who <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing iust,</hi>
               <note place="margin">8.</note> 
               <hi>died for vs vniuſt: who, when as yet we were ſinners,</hi>
               <note place="margin">10.</note> 
               <hi>died for vs: who, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> we were Gods enimies, reconciled vs vnto him by hys owne death, that by hys life,</hi> we being reconciled, might be ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued. If therefore wee thus loue, as <hi>Chriſt</hi> hath loued vs, <hi>vnfaynedly, ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerely,</hi> and <hi>freely, without all regarde of merite,</hi>
               <note n="c" place="margin">Ephe. 5.2,</note> then <hi>walke we in loue, then are we followers of Gods as beloued children</hi>
               <note n="d" place="margin">Act. 11.26.</note> we are called <hi>Chriſtians</hi> of <hi>chriſt,</hi> let vs reſemble him in maners, els are we, our name notwithſtanding, mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, we take our ſelues to bee the <hi>Diſciples</hi> of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> let vs then learne to practiſe the precepte of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> which he teacheth vs ſaying:<note n="e" place="margin">Io. 13.34.</note> 
               <hi>A new commaundement giue I vnto you, that ye loue one an other: as I haue loued you, that yee alſo loue one an
<pb facs="tcp:19080:31" rendition="simple:additions"/> other.</hi> VVe would be all reputed the children of our <hi>father, <hi>that is in heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</hi>
               </hi> But<note n="a" place="margin">Mat. 5.45.</note> 
               <hi>he maketh his ſunne to ariſe on the euill, and the good: and ſendeth rayne <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n the iuſt, and vniuſt. Let vs then: that we may be his children,</hi>
               <note n="b" place="margin">Mat. 5.44.</note> 
               <hi>loue our enni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies: bleſſe them that curſe vs: doe good to them that hate vs: and pray for them that hurt and perſecute vs.</hi> Let vs con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider (as <hi>Chriſt</hi> teacheth vs)<note n="c" place="margin">Mat. 5.46.</note> that <hi>if we loue them, which loue vs, we ſhall haue no revvard: for the publicans do euen the ſame.</hi>
               <note place="margin">47</note> 
               <hi>And if vvee be friendly to our brethren onely, vve doe no ſinguler thing: for euen the Publicans do likevviſe.</hi>
               <note place="margin">48</note> But <hi>we muſt be perfect, as our Father, whiche is in heauen, is perfect.</hi> Neither can there be any precept fuller of equitie, then this:<note n="d" place="margin">Ephe. 5.2</note> 
               <hi>Walke in loue, euen as Chriſt hath loued vs:</hi> Wherein it is required, that we, whiche are beloued of <hi>God</hi> in <hi>Chriſt,</hi> ſhould loue our bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, whom, the <hi>Father</hi> loueth in the <hi>Sonne,</hi> as tenderly as hee loueth vs. And thus haue I taught you, my bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, folowing <hi>Paules</hi> ſteppes in this place, by the example both of the <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:19080:32" rendition="simple:additions"/> and of the <hi>Sonne,</hi> what manne<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of loue <hi>God</hi> requireth at our handes that we may proue<note n="a" place="margin">Ephe. 5.1,</note> 
               <hi>followers of him as deare children.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note n="*" place="margin">2. By proof of this exam<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ple.</note>Now foloweth in the texte the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond way, whereby <hi>Paule</hi> deſcribet<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the manner of loue, by the practiſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> whereof wee become followers o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>God,</hi> when as hee ſayth:<note n="b" place="margin">Ephe. 5.2</note> 
               <hi>And hat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> giuen himſelfe for vs <hi>(to be)</hi> an offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, and a ſacrifice of a ſweet ſmel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, ſauour to God.</hi>
               <note n="c" place="margin">Ephe. 5.2</note> 
               <hi>Paul</hi> hauyng laſtly propoſed <hi>Chriſt</hi> himſelfe vnto vs, as a perfect paterne, after y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> which we muſt faſhion that our loue, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in wee muſt walke, that wee may be found<note n="d" place="margin">Ephe. 5.2</note> 
               <hi>followers</hi> of <hi>God, <hi>as deare chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren,</hi>
               </hi> forgetteth not, to proue vnto vs the perfection of the paterne of our i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, (I mean of the loue of <hi>chriſt</hi>) by the excellent effecte, whiche came thereof, namely our full, and perfect redemption,<note n="e" place="margin">Heb. 9.25,</note> wrought by the oblati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of <hi>Chriſt</hi> heere mentioned. The rule of <hi>Chriſt</hi> is<note n="f" place="margin">Mat. 7.17.12.33. Luc. 6.43.44</note> that the tree is knowne by the frute, ſo that the bad fruit ſheweth the tree to be bad, and
<pb facs="tcp:19080:32" rendition="simple:additions"/> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he good fruite ſheweth the tree to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ee good. Then followeth it, that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he loue of <hi>Chriſt</hi> to vs-wardes is moſt perfect,<note n="a" place="margin">Ioh. 3.16,</note> the fruite whereof is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ur ſaluation and euerlaſting life. yet <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>till note, beloued, that the loue of Chriſt is here propoſed vnto vs, not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o muche to bee contemplated (al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hough it deſerue a moſt reuerend co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>templation) as to be imitated. But forſomuche as vnder this effecte of <hi>Chriſtes</hi> loue,<note n="b" place="margin">Ioh. 13.1</note> 
               <hi>wherewith he loued vs vnto the end,</hi> the worke of our whole <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>edemption offereth it ſelfe to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered, it ſhall behoue me, following my texte, to deliuer the ſame vnto you (as God ſhall inhable me) more par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly.<note n="*" place="margin">In our re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption, wrought by a ſacrifice, 6. circumſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces to bee-noted.</note> The effect of <hi>Chriſtes</hi> loue towardes vs, (as I haue ſayd)<note n="c" place="margin">Ioh. 3.15.</note> is our redemption, and our redemption is wrought by a ſacrifice, and in this ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice, (as <hi>Paule</hi> here deſcribeth it,) <hi>Sixe circumſtances are to be conſidered:</hi> The firſt, <hi>who was the ſacrificer:</hi> The ſecond, <hi>How he ſacrificed:</hi> The third,<note place="margin">14</note> 
               <hi>what, and of what kind the ſacrifice was:</hi> The fourth, <hi>For whom it was ſacrificed:</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:19080:33" rendition="simple:additions"/> The fifth, <hi>To whome it was ſacrificed</hi> The ſixt, <hi>what effecte the ſacrific<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> wrought.</hi> VVhen I ſhall briefly hau<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> intreated ſeuerally of theſe <hi>ſix point<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> I will conclude, and commit you <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the grace of <hi>God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note n="*" place="margin">1. Chriſt is the ſacrifice,</note>
               <hi>Man</hi> was created by GOD in the beginning<note n="a" place="margin">Gen. 1, 26,</note> 
               <hi>after his image an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſimilitude,</hi>
               <note n="b" place="margin">Ephe. 4, 24.</note> 
               <hi>in righteouſneſſe and tr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> holineſſe.</hi> But alas through the fall <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Adam</hi> in <hi>Man</hi> the image and ſimil<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tude of <hi>God</hi> is defaced, and his rig<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>teouſneſſe, and true holineſſe is clea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> blotted out,<note n="c" place="margin">Ephe. 2.1.3,</note> ſo that now <hi>vve are de<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> in our treſpaſſes and ſinns, being by natu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the children of wrath,</hi>
               <note n="d" place="margin">Rom, 3, 23,</note> 
               <hi>and depriued the glory of <hi>God.</hi>
               </hi> Nowe let vs conſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>der the mercy of <hi>God.</hi> VVhen w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> were not able, by our owne pow<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> to deliuer oure ſelues from this v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſpeakable miſerie,<note place="margin">phe. 1, 4,</note> into the which th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rough ſinne wee were fallen, <hi>e Go<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> had deuiſed, <hi>before the foundation of t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> world,</hi> to reſtore vs to libertie, by a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> holye conciliation to bee made b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>twene him and vs. But let vs co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſider how the caſe ſtoode, <hi>God</hi> ke<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:19080:33"/> his couenaunt, which hee made with <hi>Man: Man</hi> brake the couenant, which hee made with <hi>God. God</hi> the <hi>Creator</hi> was offended: <hi>Man</hi> the <hi>Creature</hi> had offended. God needed not to ſeeke a reconciliation with <hi>Man,</hi>
               <note n="a" place="margin">Rom. 1.25</note> who of him ſelfe without <hi>Man</hi> is <hi>bleſſed: Man</hi> durſt not ſeeke a reconciliation, with <hi>God,</hi> who of him-ſelfe without <hi>God,</hi>
               <note n="b" place="margin">Leu. 27, 26 Gal. 3.10.</note> is <hi>curſſed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Two thinges in the Sacrifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cer to be noted, 1, his Subſtance, 2 his Office.</note>Who then might become a fitte mediatour of peace, as wel in reſpect of his ſubſtance or perſon, as of his function or office? Behold <hi>the</hi>
               <note n="c" place="margin">Ro. 16.25.</note> 
               <hi>reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation of the miſterie, vvhich vvas kept ſecret ſince the world began,</hi>
               <note n="d" place="margin">1. Cor. 2.7.8.</note> 
               <hi>euen the hid vviſedome, vvhich <hi>God</hi> had deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined before the vvorlde, vnto our glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rye, vvhiche none of the Princes of this vvorld hath knovven.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note n="*" place="margin">1, The Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crificer by his ſubſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce or perſon is god &amp; man,</note> 
               <note n="e" place="margin">Gal. 4, 4.5.</note>
               <hi>When the fulneſſe of time vvas com, God ſent forth his ſonne, made of a vvo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, made vnder the lavv, that he might redeeme vs, vvhiche vvere vnder the lavve, that vve might receiue the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doption of Sonnes.</hi> This was a fit me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diatour, an apt reconcyler, a conue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nient
<pb facs="tcp:19080:34" rendition="simple:additions"/> daies-man betweene <hi>god</hi> and <hi>Man.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Chriſt, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing God, hable to ſaue vs.</note> For beeing<note n="a" place="margin">Mat. 1.23,</note> 
               <hi>god</hi> euen the<note n="b" place="margin">pſal. 2.7. Ioan. 3.16.</note> 
               <hi>Sonne</hi> of <hi>god,</hi> hee durſt preſente him ſelfe before <hi>god</hi> his <hi>Father,</hi> to intreat for <hi>Man,</hi>
               <note n="c" place="margin">Phil. 2.6.</note> 
               <hi>as one vvhich thought it no robberie to bee equall vvith <hi>god:</hi>
               </hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Chriſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yng Man willyng to ſaue vs.</note> And beeing<note n="d" place="margin">Matt. 1.18. Luc. 2.7.</note> Man<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> euen the <hi>Son</hi> of <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie</hi> the virgin, was willing to recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cile <hi>Man</hi> vnto <hi>god,</hi>
               <note n="e" place="margin">Heb. 4.15.</note> as one which was touched with the feeling of our infirmities. And ſo in the perſon of the atonement-maker, was fulfilled the deuine prophecy of <hi>Eſay,</hi> ſaying:<note n="f" place="margin">Eſa. 7.14. Mat. 1.23.</note> 
               <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holde, a virgin ſhall bee with childe &amp; ſhall Beare a Son, and they ſhall call his name Emanuell, which is by interpretation, god with vs.</hi> And this is hee which is the Sacrificer,<note n="g" place="margin">Pſal, 2, 7, Heb. 5.5.</note> 
               <hi>god</hi> with <hi>god</hi> and<note n="h" place="margin">Phil, 2.7.</note> 
               <hi>Man</hi> with <hi>Man</hi>
               <note n="i" place="margin">Ion. 6.51.</note> one <hi>Chriſt,</hi>
               <note n="k" place="margin">Pſal, 2, 7,</note> the <hi>Sonne</hi> of <hi>god,</hi>
               <note n="l" place="margin">Mat. 3, 17. Mar. 1, 11.</note> the ſecond perſon in the bleſſed <hi>Trini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie.</hi> Nowe this much being ſpoken of the <hi>perſon</hi> and <hi>ſubſtaunce</hi> of the <hi>Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficer,</hi> let vs nowe more neerely way, who, and how great hee is by the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration of his <hi>Function</hi> and <hi>office,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note n="*" place="margin">The Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crificer, by his function or Office, is Chriſt, ſo called for that he is: 1, our Prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te: 2, our Chriſt: 3. our King,</note>None was found fit, (as yee haue
<pb facs="tcp:19080:34" rendition="simple:additions"/> heard) to bee the <hi>Sacrificer</hi> to <hi>God</hi> for <hi>Man,</hi> but the onely <hi>Sone</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> who in reſpect of his <hi>function or office,</hi> is cal<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>led the Meſhiah, <hi>Chriſt</hi> the <hi>Annoyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted.</hi> This name the word of <hi>God</hi> at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tributeth<note n="a" place="margin">1. Kin. 19.16</note> to <hi>Prophets,</hi>
               <note n="b" place="margin">Leu, 16, 32 Num, 3, 3,</note> 
               <hi>Prieſts,</hi> and<note n="c" place="margin">Iud. 9.8, 1, Sam. 9, 16, 01, 1,</note> 
               <hi>Kinges,</hi> as well becauſe they were annointed with materiall oyle, (in token of ſpirituall graces, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with <hi>god</hi> had indued them for the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecuting of their offices) as alſo for that they were figures of <hi>Chriſt</hi> then to come. But this name agreeth pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly to our <hi>redeemer,</hi> whome <hi>god <hi>an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nointed,</hi>
               </hi> not with materiall oyle, but<note n="d" place="margin">Pſal, 45, 8, 89, 21,</note> 
               <hi>with the oile of gladneſſe aboue his fellows</hi> that is, with the full meaſure of his ſpiritual graces, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he being our great <hi>Prophet,</hi> our high <hi>Prieſt,</hi> and our migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie <hi>King,</hi> might bee a fit Sacrificer to reconcile vs vnto <hi>god.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note n="*" place="margin">1 Chriſt our Prophet,</note>Neceſſarie it was, that the <hi>Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficer,</hi> ſhould bee the <hi>Prophet</hi> of <hi>gods</hi> people, that<note n="e" place="margin">Eſa, 1, 16, 1, Luc, 4.18,</note> the <hi>Spirite of the Lorde being vppon him, hee might therefore annoynt him, that hee ſhould preache the Goſpell to the poore: hee might ſend him,
<pb facs="tcp:19080:35" rendition="simple:additions"/> that he ſhold heal the broken harted that he ſhold Preach deliuerance to the Capti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues and recouering of ſight to the blinde that he ſhould ſet at libertie them, that are bruſed:</hi>
               <note place="margin">19.</note> 
               <hi>And that hee ſhoulde preach the acceptable yeare of the Lord:</hi> that hee knowing the will of his <hi>Father</hi> in our reco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ciliation,<note n="a" place="margin">Heb, 10, 9,</note> ſhould do the ſame.</p>
            <p>
               <note n="*" place="margin">2, Chriſt our Prieſt,</note>Neceſſary it was that the <hi>Sacrifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cer</hi> ſhould bee the <hi>Priest</hi> of <hi>gods</hi> peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, that ſince<note n="b" place="margin">Pſal, 40.7, Heb, 10, 6,</note> 
               <hi>god <hi>had no pleaſure in burnt offrings,</hi>
               </hi>
               <note place="margin">10:</note> 
               <hi>&amp; ſin offrings he might of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer his body in ſacrifice to <hi>god</hi> the <hi>fathe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> &amp; ſo do his vvill,</hi>
               <note place="margin">9</note> 
               <hi>by the which we are ſa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tified:</hi>
               <note place="margin">10,</note> 
               <note place="margin">4.</note> And for that <hi>it was impoſſible, that the blood of bulles and goates ſhould take away ſinnes,</hi>
               <note n="c" place="margin">1, Pet. 1, 18,</note> 
               <hi>he might redeem vs, with his precious blood,</hi>
               <note place="margin">19,</note> 
               <hi>being a lambe vndefi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, and vvithout ſpotte: And finally,</hi>
               <note n="d" place="margin">Heb, 10, 12</note> 
               <hi>that after he had offered one ſacrifice for ſinnes: he might ſit for euer at the right hand of God,</hi>
               <note place="margin">13,</note> 
               <hi>and from thence-foorth tarrie till his enimies ſhould be made hys foot-ſtoole.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note n="*" place="margin">3 Chriſt, our King,</note>Neceſſarie it was, that the <hi>ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficer</hi> ſhould be the <hi>king</hi> of <hi>gods</hi> people<note n="e" place="margin">Io, 16, 33,</note> to <hi>ouer-come</hi> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 
               <hi>world,</hi>
               <note n="f" place="margin">Luc, 22, 42</note> to <hi>ſubdue</hi> the
<pb facs="tcp:19080:35" rendition="simple:additions"/> 
               <hi>fleſh,</hi>
               <note n="a" place="margin">Mat, 4, 1, &amp;c. Mar, 1, 12, &amp;c Luc: 4, 1, &amp;c,</note> to <hi>conquer <hi>Satan,</hi>
               </hi>
               <note n="b" place="margin">Io, 8, 46,</note> to <hi>vanquiſh ſinne,</hi>
               <note n="c" place="margin">Rom, 5, 2,</note> to <hi>pacifie <hi>gods</hi> wrath,</hi>
               <note n="d" place="margin">Oſe, 13, 14 1, Co. 15, 54,</note> to <hi>plucke</hi> out the <hi>ſting</hi> of <hi>deeth,</hi>
               <note place="margin">55,</note> to <hi>ſpoyle hell of her victorie</hi>
               <note n="e" place="margin">Pſa, 68, 19, Eph, 4, 8,</note> to <hi>leade captiuitie captiue,</hi> to <hi>giue giftes vnto men,</hi>
               <note n="f" place="margin">Pſa, 110, 1, mat, 22, 44,</note> and <hi>to triumph ouer all hys enimies:</hi>
               <note n="g" place="margin">Io, 10, 4.</note> yea to <hi>direct</hi> vs his people with his <hi>vvord,</hi>
               <note n="h" place="margin">10, 22,</note> to guide vs by his <hi>ſpirite,</hi>
               <note n="i" place="margin">Pſal, 2, 9,</note> to <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend</hi> vs by his <hi>povver,</hi>
               <note n="k" place="margin">Luc, 1, 32,</note> 
               <hi>vnto vvhome <hi>god</hi> gaue the throne of his <hi>Father Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid,</hi>
               </hi>
               <note place="margin">33,</note> 
               <hi>that hee might raigne ouer the houſe of <hi>Iacob</hi> for euer, that of his kingdome ſhoulde be none ende.</hi> And thus ye haue heard my beloued, the ordinance of God, that whom the ſacrificer ſhould reconcile vnto God, them ſhould he inſtruct, as their <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet, ſanctifie</hi> as their <hi>Prieſt,</hi> and <hi>guide,</hi> as their <hi>King.</hi> Iudge ye then, whether the <hi>Papiſtes</hi> be not of the number of thoſe falſe teachers, whome <hi>Peter</hi> prophecied ſhould come,<note n="l" place="margin">2, Pet. 2.1,</note> 
               <hi>vvhiche ſhould denie the</hi> Lord <hi>that bought them,</hi> which vndoubtedly they doe, when by bringing in the <hi>traditions</hi> of men, they denie the <hi>fulneſſe</hi> of <hi>Chriſtes</hi> prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie: by ſetting vp their <hi>ſacrifice</hi> of the
<pb facs="tcp:19080:36" rendition="simple:additions"/> 
               <hi>Maſſe,</hi> they deny y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 
               <hi>fulneſſe</hi> of <hi>Chriſtes <hi>Prieſt-hood:</hi>
               </hi> by mayntayning, that the <hi>Biſhop</hi> of <hi>Rome</hi> is <hi>Chriſtes <hi>vicar generall</hi>
               </hi> vpon earth, they deny the <hi>ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe</hi> of <hi>Chriſtes <hi>kingdome.</hi>
               </hi> But let them take heede and repent in time, otherwiſe (according to <hi>Peters</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination)<note n="a" place="margin">2. Pet, 2, 1.</note> 
               <hi>they vvill hring vppon themſelues ſvvift damnation.</hi> And this much concerning the <hi>ſacrificer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note n="*" place="margin">2, Chriſt ſacrificed vo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>luntarily wil<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>yngly, &amp; of his owne ac</note>Nowe commeth to bee conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, the ſecond circumſtance of our re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption, <hi>hovv, and vvith vvhat mind this ſacrificer ſacrificed.</hi> And that is, <hi>hee ſacrificed voluntarily, vvillingly, and, of his ovvn accorde.</hi> That this perſwaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on might bee ſetled in oure heartes, <hi>Paule</hi> ſayth not: (as truely hee might) <hi>Chriſt</hi> redeemed vs, or reconciled vs to <hi>God,</hi> but, when he hadde ſaid:<note n="b" place="margin">Eph, 5, 2,</note> 
               <hi>Chriſt loued vs,</hi> to ſhew the wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full excellencie, and incomprehenſible meaſure of his loue towardes vs, hee addeth:<note n="c" place="margin">Eph, 5.2,</note> 
               <hi>And gaue himſelfe for vs.</hi> So was the prophecie of <hi>Dauid,</hi> concerning <hi>Chriſtes <hi>voluntary death,</hi>
               </hi> fulfilled, reported by the author of the
<pb facs="tcp:19080:36" rendition="simple:additions"/> Epiſtle to the <hi>Hebrues</hi> in this ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner:<note n="a" place="margin">Pſ, 4, 7.8.9 Heb, 10, 15,</note> 
               <hi>Wherefore, when Chriſt commeth into the world, he ſayth: Sacrifice, and offering thou wouldſt not: but a body haſt thou ordayned me: In burnt offringes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">6,</note> 
               <hi>and ſinne offrings thou haſt had no pleaſure.</hi>
               <note place="margin">7</note> 
               <hi>Then I ſayd, Loe, I come, (in the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of the booke it is written of me,) that I ſhoulde doe thy will, O God.</hi> And thy will is, that hee ſhould <hi>voluntarily</hi> die for vs. In th <hi>10</hi> of Iohn, where <hi>Chriſt</hi> teacheth vs, that<note n="b" place="margin">Io, 10, 11</note> he is the good ſhepheard, and that we are his ſheepe, to teſtifie hys prompt minde to die for vs, hee pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounceth, that whereas<note n="c" place="margin">Io. 10, 18,</note> 
               <hi>no man could take his life from him, hee layde it dovvne of himſelfe, for his ſheepe.</hi> If any obiect and ſay: Yea but when Chriſt ſaw, that his bitter death approched, comparing it to<note n="d" place="margin">Mat, 26, 39 mar, 14, 36, Luc, 22, 42,</note> a cuppe, he prayed his <hi>Father,</hi> that, <hi>if it vvere poſsible it might paſſe from him:</hi> Howe then was his death voluntary, ſince gladly hee would eſchewe it? I aunſwere: this ſpeache of <hi>Chriſt</hi> ſheweth not any vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>willingneſſe
<pb facs="tcp:19080:37" rendition="simple:additions"/> to dye for vs, but the truth of both his natures, humane and diuine, and his willingneſſe to offer himſelfe in ſacrifice for our redemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. For in that, <hi>Chriſt</hi> was ſubiect to humane affections and paſſions<note n="a" place="margin">Mat. 26 38</note> as <hi>heauineſſe,</hi>
               <note n="b" place="margin">Mar. 14, 33.</note> 
               <hi>trouble of minde,</hi>
               <note n="c" place="margin">Luc. 22.44</note> and <hi>agonie,</hi> (into the which he fel, not ſo much through the terrour of death approching, as the ſenſible feeling of <hi>Gods</hi> wrath then begon to be layd vppon him for our ſinnes) it ſheweth, that he was a true and a natural man (⸪) But in that hee ſubdueth the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmitie of the fleſhe,<note n="*" place="margin">Mar. 26, 39 42. mar. 14.36. Lu, 22, 42</note> and ſubmitteth his will to the will of his <hi>Father,</hi> hee ſheweth himſelfe to be <hi>god,</hi> who be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing conceiued, as touching his <hi>man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood,</hi> without ſinne, moderateth hys humayne affections, in ſuch a tempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rature, by the power of his <hi>god-head</hi> that, although hee were ſubiect vnto them, yet they brake not out to rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lion againſt <hi>god,</hi> but were preſerued without blemiſhe of ſinne. And laſtly he willingly yeeldeth to <hi>gods</hi> deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination, and voluntarily ſubmitteth
<pb facs="tcp:19080:37" rendition="simple:additions"/> himſelfe to the death of the croſſe, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluding his prayer:<note n="a" place="margin">Mat 16.39</note> 
               <hi>Neuertheleſſe not as <hi>I</hi> will, but as thou wilt:</hi>
               <note n="b" place="margin">Mar. 14, 3</note> 
               <hi>Not that <hi>I</hi> will, but that thou wilt:</hi>
               <note n="c" place="margin">Luc. 22.42</note> 
               <hi>Not my will, but thine be done.</hi> Ye ſee then, that the manner of his ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crificing, was by a <hi>vvilling</hi> and a <hi>vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luntary death.</hi> Oh the exceeding loue of <hi>Chriſt</hi> to vs-ward,<note n="d" place="margin">Rom. 5, 8,</note> 
               <hi>vvho vvhen vve vvere yet ſinners died for vs.</hi>
               <note n="e" place="margin">Io. 15.13.</note> 
               <hi>Greater loue than this hath no manne, vvhen any man beſtoweth his life for hys friendes. But vvee are the friendes of <hi>Chriſt,</hi>
               </hi>
               <note place="margin">14</note> 
               <hi>if we doe vvhatſoeuer he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundeth vs.</hi> And this is his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundement, that<note n="f" place="margin">Io. 15, 12,</note> 
               <hi>vve loue one an other as he hath loued vs.</hi> But he lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued vs with an <hi>vnfayned</hi> loue, whiche of his owne accorde gaue himſelfe for vs. Let vs therefore loue one an other <hi>vnfaynedly,</hi> as beſeemeth the <hi>diſciples</hi> of <hi>Ieſus Chriſt.</hi> And this may ſuffice to be ſpoken of the <hi>maner</hi> of the ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficing of <hi>Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note n="*" place="margin">3. The ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice was the innocent ſoule, the vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>defiled body &amp; the preci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous blood of Chriſt.</note>Now in the third place the <hi>ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice it ſelfe</hi> commeth to be conſidered.</p>
            <p>
               <note n="*" place="margin">3. The ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice was the innocent ſoule, the vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>defiled body &amp; the preci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous blood of Chriſt.</note>Heerein muſt bee noted two
<pb facs="tcp:19080:38" rendition="simple:additions"/> things:<note place="margin">Two things noted.</note> Firſt, the <hi>ſubſtance,</hi> then the <hi>qualities</hi> of this ſacrifice, that thereby we may learne: both <hi>vvhat</hi> it is, and of <hi>what kinde</hi> it is.</p>
            <p>
               <note n="*" place="margin">1, The ſub<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtance of the Sacrifice is the man-head of Chriſt.</note>Of the <hi>Subſtance</hi> of this ſacrifice <hi>Paule</hi> ſpeaketh in this texte, when as he telleth vs, that<note n="a" place="margin">Eph. 5.2,</note> 
               <hi>Chriſt <hi>gaue hym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe for vs.</hi>
               </hi> So then: looke what <hi>chriſt</hi> is, as touching his <hi>Man-head,</hi> and that is the ſacrifice offered for vs. But <hi>Chriſt,</hi> according to his humanitie, ſtandeth of a reaſonable ſoule, and an humane body. Therefore it followeth, that he gaue his ſoule,<note n="*" place="margin">Chriſts ſoule giuen to redeme our ſoules, his body, for our bodyes.</note> to redeeme our ſoules, and his body, to redeeme our bodies. Body for body, and ſoule for ſoule<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> yea, he gaue for vs<note n="b" place="margin">Mat. 27.35</note> his <hi>body,</hi> to be crucified:<note n="c" place="margin">Ion. 19, 34</note> his bloud, to be ſhed<note n="d" place="margin">Ion. 19 03</note> his ſoule to bee ſeperated:<note n="e" place="margin">Ion. 19, 33</note> hys life, to be yealded. So then ſo tender<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly did <hi>Chriſt</hi> loue vs, that<note n="f" place="margin">Pet<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 18.19</note> 
               <hi>he redee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med vs, not with corruptible thinges, ſil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer and golde:<note place="margin">20,</note> but with his owne pretious bloud, as of a lambe vndefiled, and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſpot. Which was ordeined before the foundation of the worlde, but was decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red in the laſt times for our ſakes.</hi> Ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb facs="tcp:19080:38" rendition="simple:additions"/> was there anie thing fitte to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come the <hi>ſacrifice</hi> for <hi>ſinne:</hi> but the <hi>Sonne</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> being free from ſinne. For although the <hi>ſacrifices</hi> of the law were ordayned by <hi>God,</hi> yet<note n="a" place="margin">Heb. 10, 4,</note> 
               <hi>was it vnpoſsible, that by the bloud of bulles and goates, our ſinnes ſhould be taken away.</hi> And although <hi>Angels</hi> be moſt excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent creatures of <hi>God,</hi> yet was the nature of none of them fit for this <hi>ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice.</hi> And therfore y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 
               <hi>Sonne</hi> of <hi>god</hi> tooke not vpon him<note n="b" place="margin">Heb. 2, 16,</note> the nature of an <hi>Angell,</hi> but of<note n="c" place="margin">Luc. 1, 35,</note> 
               <hi>Man,</hi> that in hys <hi>Manhead,</hi> hee might reconcile <hi>Man</hi> vnto <hi>god,</hi>
               <note n="d" place="margin">Gen. 2.6.</note> as in <hi>Man-head Man</hi> fell from <hi>god.</hi> This was the onely way to ſatiſfie <hi>gods</hi> iuſtice, and to pacifie his wrath, that<note n="e" place="margin">Rom. 5.19.</note> 
               <hi>as by the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>obedience of one Man <hi>Adam;</hi> many wer made ſinners: So by the obedience of one Man, <hi>chriſt,</hi>
               </hi>
               <note place="margin">12,</note> 
               <hi>many might alſo bee made righteous: * And that, as, by one Man <hi>Adam,</hi> ſinne entered into the worlde, and death by ſinne: * So, by one man <hi>Chriſt<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </hi> we might receiue the attonement, tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rough the remiſsion of ſinnes, to euerla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting life.</hi> Of this point intreateth
<pb facs="tcp:19080:39" rendition="simple:additions"/> 
               <hi>Paule</hi> more at large in the fifth to the <hi>Romanes,</hi> a ſcripture for this pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe diligently to bee wayed. And thus ye fee, that onely <hi>chriſt</hi>
               <note n="a" place="margin">Reuel. 5.5.</note> 
               <hi>the Lion, which is of the tribe of Iudah, and the roote of Dauid, is worthy to open the booke of life, and to loſe the ſeuen ſeales of the Myſteries of the kingdome of heauen<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi>
               <note n="b" place="margin">Io. 1, 29.</note> 
               <hi>euen the lambe of <hi>god,</hi> whiche taketh away but ſinnes<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi>
               <note n="c" place="margin">Reuel. 5.6.</note> 
               <hi>the lambe of <hi>god,</hi> which was killed for vs:</hi>
               <note n="d." place="margin">1. Pet. 1.20.</note> 
               <hi>the lambe of God, which is a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ordayned for vs, before the foundation of the world.</hi> And for con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion of this point marke, I beſeech you this myſterie in our reconciliati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, that he onely is the <hi>ſacrifice,</hi> who onely is the <hi>ſacrificer, Chriſt</hi> the one, <hi>Chriſt</hi> the other,<note n="e" place="margin">Rom. 5.1, Heb. 10 14.</note> who by himſelfe hath reconciled vs to <hi>god</hi> his <hi>father.</hi> Therfore blame vs not, although we dare not teach (as doe the <hi>Papiſts</hi> moſt blaſphemouſly) that <hi>Chriſt</hi> is offered in the Lordes ſupper, by the miniſter to <hi>god,</hi> for our ſinnes,<note n="f" place="margin">Heb. 9.26.</note> 
               <hi>(who in the ende of the vvorld, vvas made manifeſt once, to put avvay ſinne: by the ſacrifice of himſelfe,)</hi> but beleue vs, when wee
<pb facs="tcp:19080:39" rendition="simple:additions"/> teach, that<note n="a" place="margin">Luc. 22, 19 1. Cor. 11.24 25</note> 
               <hi>thereby the memory of his death is continued vntill his comming,</hi> according to the inſtitution of <hi>Christ</hi> himſelfe. Now ſince <hi>Chriſt</hi> hath loued vs, more than hee hath loued his <hi>body,</hi> his <hi>bloud,</hi> his <hi>ſoule,</hi> his <hi>life,</hi> all the which he gaue for<note n="b" place="margin">1, Co. 6.20,</note> the price of our redemption,<note place="margin">7, 23.</note> let vs loue one an other<note n="c" place="margin">Eph. 5.2.</note> 
               <hi>as hee hath loued vs, and ſo become the followers of God as deare children.</hi> And this much concernyng the <hi>Subſtance</hi> of the <hi>Sacrifice,</hi> which is Chriſt him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe.</p>
            <p>
               <note n="*" place="margin">2, The qua<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lities of the ſacrifice were an ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly oblation &amp; an obedi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ent ſuff<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>yng-</note> 
               <note n="d" place="margin">Heb. 10.1.</note>
               <hi>The ceremoniall lavve had the ſhadovv of good thinges to come, and not the verie image of the thinges.</hi> There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>Paule</hi> knowing, that<note n="e" place="margin">Rom. 10.4.</note> 
               <hi>Chriſt</hi> is the ende of the lawe,<note n="f" place="margin">Mat. 5.17.</note> (whiche hathe fulfilled the law of commandementes through his obedience,<note n="g" place="margin">Eph. 2.14.</note> and perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, what ſoeuer was figured in the law of ceremonies, for our redempti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on) calleth him in this text<note n="h" place="margin">Ephe. 5.2.</note> an <hi>offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring,</hi> and a <hi>Sacrifice.</hi> The kindes of <hi>Sacrificers</hi> in the lawe of <hi>Moſes</hi> were manie and ſundry, not deuiſed by <hi>Men,</hi>
               <note n="i" place="margin">Leu. 1.1. Num. 7.89.</note> but ordayned by <hi>god,</hi> to ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifie
<pb facs="tcp:19080:40" rendition="simple:additions"/> partly the filthineſſe of ſinne in vs,<note n="a" place="margin">Eſa, 59, 2,</note> 
               <hi>vvhereby vvee be deuided from <hi>god,</hi>
               </hi> and partly the expiation of ſinne through <hi>Christ,</hi>
               <note n="b" place="margin">Heb, 9, 14,</note> 
               <hi>vvhereby vve be reconciled vnto <hi>god.</hi>
               </hi> All theſe kyndes <hi>Paule</hi> reduceth vnto two:<note n="c" place="margin">Eph. 5.2.</note> An <hi>obla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> and an <hi>hoaſt,</hi> both the whiche hee termeth <hi>Chriſt</hi> to be. And not without cauſe. For ſuch was <hi>Christ</hi> the ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice in true performance, as wer theſe in ſhadowed figure. So by the nature of them, we may learne the <hi>qualities</hi> of the ſacrifice, which is <hi>Chriſt.</hi> For firſt <hi>Paul</hi> calleth <hi>Christ</hi>
               <note n="d" place="margin">Eph. 5.2.</note> 
               <hi>Proſphoran,</hi> an <hi>oblation,</hi> an holy offering: Secondly he calleth him <hi>Thuſian</hi> an <hi>hoſt,</hi> a ſlayne ſacrifice. By the firſt, we learn <hi>Chriſtes</hi>
               <note n="e" place="margin">Luc, 1, 35,</note> 
               <hi>holineſſe,</hi> by the ſecond wee learne <hi>Christes</hi>
               <note n="f" place="margin">Pſal, 22, 1, Mar. 27, 46, Mar. 15.34,</note> 
               <hi>ſuffering.</hi> It was meete, that this ſacrifice ſhoulde be <hi>holy,</hi> that it might ſanctifie the vnho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly: It was meete, that this ſacrifice ſhuld ſuffer, that it might beare <hi>gods</hi> wrath due for ſinne. The offering in the olde lawe, is therfore reputed ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, becauſe it was ſuch, as <hi>god,</hi> which is holy, appointed to bee offered. The
<pb facs="tcp:19080:40" rendition="simple:additions"/> ſlayn ſacrifice in the ſame law, is iuſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly termed to ſuffer, becauſe it was a ſenſible beaſt, or a ſenſible birde, ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poynted by God to be ſlayne. Muche might be ſayde of the figures, whcich are theſe, but, for want of time, I will onely ſpeake of the trueth, whiche is <hi>Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Two qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities of the Sacrifice to be conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red.</note>And in him, two things here are to be conſidered: Firſt his <hi>Holineſſe,</hi> Secondly, his <hi>ſuffering.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note n="*" place="margin">1. Chriſts holines.</note>It was moſt neceſſarie, that this ſacrifice ſhuld be holy, for otherwiſe<note n="a" place="margin">Mat. 5.13, Mar. 9.50. Luc. 14, 34,</note> it had not bene fit, to haue bene offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to the moſt holy God: It had not benefit, to put away our vnholineſſe. It had not bene fit, to haue ſanctified vs. If the ſalt in it ſelfe had not ſalt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe,<note n="a" place="margin">Mat. 5.13, Mar. 9.50. Luc. 14, 34,</note> it could not ſeaſon the things that it ſeaſoneth. If the fire in it ſelfe had not heat, it coulde not heate thoſe things which ar before it. If y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſun in it ſelf had not light, it could not ligh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten the ſuperioure and inferiour bodyes. No more coulde this ſacrifice <hi>Chriſt,</hi> make vs holie in the ſight of <hi>god,</hi> were it not that it is holy of it
<pb facs="tcp:19080:41" rendition="simple:additions"/> ſelfe. For if reaſon require, that the thing, which is to imparte <hi>a</hi> qualitie with another, bee firſt fully indued with the ſame it ſelfe, then muſt it neceſſarily be required, that <hi>Chriſt,</hi> whiche was to make vs holy, be firſt, in himſelfe, moſte holy. Nowe let vs conſider the gracious prouidence of <hi>God,</hi> to vs-ward. That <hi>Chriſt</hi> might become an holy ſacrifice, to make vs holy vnto our <hi>God,</hi>
               <note n="a" place="margin">Mar. 1.18, 20. Lu. 1.35.</note> he was concei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued without ſinne by the holy <hi>Ghoſt,</hi>
               <note n="b" place="margin">Mat. 1.25. Luc. 2.7.</note> he was borne without ſinne of the virgin <hi>Mary,</hi>
               <note n="c" place="margin">Mat. 5.17. 1. Pet. 2, 22.</note> he liued without ſin in true obedience,<note n="d" place="margin">Mat. 27.24 Luc. 23, 47,</note> he dyed without ſinne an innocent death. For theſe cauſes <hi>Chriſte</hi> is called<note n="e" place="margin">Luc, 1, 35.</note> the <hi>holye thinge,</hi>
               <note n="f" place="margin">1. Pet. 2, 9.</note> 
               <hi>by whom we are become a cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen generation, a royall prieſt-hood, and holy nation, a people ſet at liber-tie:</hi> But to what end? verily that<note n="g" place="margin">1. Pet. 2, 9.</note> 
               <hi>we ſhoulde ſhew forth the vertues of him, that hath called vs out of darkeneſſe into meruei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous light.</hi> And what? coulde we not be ſaued, were it not, that our ſacrifice <hi>Chriſt</hi> were in this abſolute manner moſt holy? No verily. For <hi>God</hi> will
<pb facs="tcp:19080:41" rendition="simple:additions"/> not that man-kind be ſaued, except by <hi>Man</hi> his law giuen to mankinde, bee fulfilled, That is, <hi>God</hi> will ſo bee found mercifull, towards mankinde, in remitting of ſinne, that he wil ſtil remayne iuſt, in requiring of man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kinde obedience to his lawes. Ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, when all mankinde was gone a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtray, ſo that<note n="a" place="margin">Ro. 3.10</note> 
               <hi>there was none righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, no not one:</hi>
               <note place="margin">11.</note> 
               <hi>None that vnderſtood, None that ſought after <hi>god,</hi>
               </hi> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 
               <hi>ſonne</hi> of <hi>god</hi> himſelfe became <hi>innocent man</hi> y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> nature of <hi>man</hi> hee might obey the lawes of <hi>God,</hi> y<hi rend="sup">t</hi>
               <note n="b" place="margin">Rom. 5, 19</note> 
               <hi>as by one mans diſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience manie were made ſinners, ſo by one mans obedience manie might be made righteous,</hi> as alſo before I proued.</p>
            <p>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Two leſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons to bee learned.</note>And here we may learne <hi>two leſſons.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note n="*" place="margin">1, the great<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>neſſe of our ſinnes,</note>The one: <hi>The greatneſſe</hi> of ſinne, which could not be put away, but by the death of the <hi>Sonne</hi> of <hi>God:</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note n="*" place="margin">2, The aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurance of our ſaluatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, Leu. 11, 44,</note>The other, the <hi>aſſurance</hi> of our ſaluation, whiche ſtandeth with the iuſtice of <hi>God.</hi> Let vs therefore ſo hope for life euerlaſting, that<note n="c" place="margin">1. Pet. 1.16.</note> 
               <hi>wee he holy, as our redeemer is holy.</hi> And this much of the firſt qualitie of the ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice, which is abſolute <hi>holineſſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:19080:42" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">2. Chriſts fferyng.</note>The ſecond qualitie of this ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice, which is <hi>Chriſt</hi> our <hi>Sauiour,</hi> is his <hi>ſuffering.</hi> This his condition <hi>Paule</hi> putteth vs in remembrance of, when in the texte, hee calleth him <hi>Thuſian,</hi> an <hi>hoaſt, a Sacrifice.</hi> The thinges whereof this <hi>ſacrifice</hi> ſtoode, was either<note n="a" place="margin">Pſa. 50.13.</note> a <hi>bull:</hi> or<note n="b" place="margin">Leu. 1.2.</note> an <hi>Oxe,</hi> or<note n="c" place="margin">3, 1,</note> an <hi>heffer:</hi> or<note n="d" place="margin">Num. 19.2</note> a <hi>calfe,</hi> or<note n="e" place="margin">Leu. 4 3.</note> a <hi>Ram</hi> or<note n="f" place="margin">Gen. 22.13</note> an <hi>ewe,</hi> or<note n="g" place="margin">Leu. 3.7.</note> a <hi>lambe,</hi> or<note n="h" place="margin">9.3.</note> a <hi>goate,</hi> or<note n="i" place="margin">1.2.</note> a turtle <hi>doue,</hi> or<note n="k" place="margin">12.8.</note> a young <hi>pigion,</hi> which was ap<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pointed by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> law, firſt to be<note n="l" place="margin">12.8.</note> 
               <hi>ſlayne,</hi> the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <note n="m" place="margin">3 2.</note> to be, <hi>offered</hi> by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> prieſt vnto <hi>god,</hi> for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſines of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> people.<note place="margin">Mat. 27.35</note> Hereby was ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied<note n="n" place="margin">Ioh. 19.34:</note> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 
               <hi>ſuffering</hi> of <hi>Chriſt,</hi>
               <note n="o" place="margin">33,</note> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 
               <hi>ſheddyng</hi> of his bloud,<note n="p" place="margin">30.</note> his <hi>death</hi> vppon the Croſſe, whereby hee might become<note n="q," place="margin">30.</note> a <hi>propitiatorie</hi> ſacrifice for the takyng away of the ſinnes of the world. The <hi>Patriarches,</hi> the <hi>Prophetes,</hi> and all the children of <hi>God,</hi> from <hi>Adam</hi> to <hi>Chriſt,</hi> as they ſet the eyes of their bo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dies in the exerciſe of religion vppon theſe ſacrifices and oblations, ſo dyd they ſet the eyes of their mindes vpon <hi>Chriſt</hi> then to come. Thus did <hi>Eſay</hi> interprete theſe ceremonies, when he foreſhewed, that<note n="t" place="margin">Eſa. 53, 3,</note> 
               <hi>Chriſt <hi>ſhoulde be
<pb facs="tcp:19080:42" rendition="simple:additions"/> ſuch a man, as ſhoulde haue a good expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience of ſorrowes and infirmities,</hi>
               </hi>
               <note place="margin">4<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </note> that <hi>Chriſt <hi>onely ſhould take on him our in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmitie, and beare our payns:</hi>
               </hi>
               <note place="margin">5</note> that <hi>Chriſt <hi>ſhould be wounded for our offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and ſmitten for our wickedneſſe:</hi>
               </hi> that <hi>the payne of our puniſhment might be layd vpon him, and that with his ſtripes we might be healed.</hi> That <hi>the <hi>Lorde would throw vppon Chriſt all our ſinnes:</hi>
               </hi>
               <note place="margin">6</note> 
               <note place="margin">7</note> That <hi>Chriſt <hi>ſhould ſuffer violence, and be euill intreated, and ſhould not open hys mouth:</hi>
               </hi> That <hi>chriſt <hi>ſhould be led as a ſheepe to be ſlayne, and yet ſhould be as ſtill as a lambe before the ſhearer, and not open his mouth:</hi>
               </hi> That <hi>chriſt <hi>ſhould be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>aken from the priſon and iudgement,</hi>
               </hi>
               <note place="margin">8</note> 
               <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hat he ſhould be cut off from the ground <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>f the liuing, which puniſhement ſhould <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oe vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> him, for the tranſgreſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of <hi>gods</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eople. That <hi>chriſt</hi> ſhould haue his graue <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>iuen him with the condempned,</hi>
               <note place="margin">9</note> 
               <hi>&amp; with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he riche man at his death: whereas hee <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ould neuer doe violence, nor vnright, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>either ſhould there be anie deceiptfulnes <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> his mouth: Neuertheleſſe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">10,</note> that <hi>it ſhould pleaſe the <hi>Lord</hi> to ſmite <hi>Chriſt</hi> with in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>mitie, that when he had made his ſoule
<pb facs="tcp:19080:43" rendition="simple:additions"/> an offering for ſinne, hee might ſee long laſting ſeede:</hi>
               <note place="margin">11</note> That <hi>Chriſt <hi>ſhould ſee the fruite and labour of his ſoule, and be ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſfied: who, being the righteous ſeruaunt of the</hi> Lorde, <hi>with his knowledge ſhoulde iustifie the multitude, for he ſhould bear their ſinnes.</hi>
               </hi>
               <note place="margin">12</note> 
               <hi>And that therefore the <hi>Lord</hi> would giue him his part among the great ones, and that he ſhould deuide the ſpoyle with the mightie, becauſe he hadde giuen ouer his ſoule to death, and was reckoned among the tranſgreſſours: which neuertheleſſe ſhould take away the ſinnes of the multitude, and make interceſſion for the miſdoers.</hi> And that I hold you not longer, dearely beloued, either in the figures, or prophecies of the old <hi>Teſtament,</hi> whiche concerne <hi>chriſtes <hi>ſuffering,</hi>
               </hi> whereby he became<note n="*" place="margin">Eph, 5, 2,</note> 
               <hi>a ſlayne ſacrifice</hi> for ſine, let vs call to minde, what thereof is reported in the <hi>New.</hi>
               <note n="a" place="margin">Ioh, 4.6.</note> Then ſhall wee finde that <hi>chriſtes</hi> whole life was a perpetuall <hi>ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring:</hi> where in he was <hi>a wearied,</hi>
               <note n="b" place="margin">mat. 21.18,</note> 
               <hi>hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gred,</hi> and<note n="c" place="margin">Io, 19.28.</note> 
               <hi>thirſted:</hi> wherein hee was<note n="d" place="margin">2.13.</note> 
               <hi>banniſhed,</hi>
               <note n="e" place="margin">Mat, 11, 18.</note> 
               <hi>ſlandered</hi> and<note n="f" place="margin">22 46, Luc. 3, 29</note> 
               <hi>perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuted:</hi> wherein hee was<note n="g" place="margin">4, 1,</note> 
               <hi>tempted</hi>
               <note n="h" place="margin">Mat. 5 2</note> 
               <hi>faſted,</hi> and<note n="i" place="margin">26, 40.</note> 
               <hi>watched:</hi> wherein hee
<pb facs="tcp:19080:43" rendition="simple:additions"/> 
               <hi>laboured,</hi>
               <note n="a" place="margin">Luc. 4.31.</note> 
               <hi>preached,</hi> and<note n="b" place="margin">22.44.</note> 
               <hi>prayed:</hi> wherein hee<note n="c" place="margin">Mat. 26, 38</note> 
               <hi>ſorowed,</hi>
               <note n="d" place="margin">Mar. 14, 33</note> 
               <hi>greeued and</hi>
               <note n="e" place="margin">Luc. 22, 44</note> 
               <hi>ſwette</hi> water and bloud: wherein he was<note n="f" place="margin">Mat. 29.49</note> 
               <hi>betraied</hi> by <hi>Iudas</hi>
               <note n="g" place="margin">Mar. 14.50</note> 
               <hi>ſorſaken</hi> by his <hi>Apoſtles</hi> and<note n="h" place="margin">Mat, 26.57</note> 
               <hi>apprehended</hi> by the ſouldiours: wherein he was with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out cauſe<note n="i" place="margin">27, 40.</note> 
               <hi>exclamed againſt</hi> wrong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully<note n="k" place="margin">Mat. 26.60</note> 
               <hi>accuſed,</hi> and vniuſtly<note n="l" place="margin">27, 24,</note> 
               <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned:</hi> wherein hee was<note n="m" place="margin">27.28.</note> 
               <hi>ſtripped,</hi>
               <note n="n" place="margin">Mat. 27.30</note> 
               <hi>buffeted,</hi> and<note n="o" place="margin">27.30.</note> 
               <hi>ſpitte vpon:</hi> wherein he was<note n="p" place="margin">Luc. 23.64</note> 
               <hi>blinde-folded,</hi>
               <note n="q" place="margin">Luc. 23, 29</note> 
               <hi>mocked,</hi> and diſdainefully<note n="r" place="margin">23, 29,</note> 
               <hi>crowned</hi> with thorns wherin he was<note n="ſ" place="margin">Mat. 27.35.</note> 
               <hi>crucified,</hi>
               <note n="t" place="margin">Mat 27.29,</note> 
               <hi>tormen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted,</hi> and<note n="u" place="margin">Io, 18, 25,</note> 
               <hi>wounded,</hi> wherein he became<note n="x" place="margin">Gal. 3, 13,</note> 
               <hi>accurſſed</hi> of God,<note n="y" place="margin">Mat. 27.46.</note> 
               <hi>ſuſteined</hi> his, <hi>wrath,</hi> and<note n="a" place="margin">Phil. 2.8.</note> 
               <hi>died a moſt ſhamfull death.</hi> But what was the cauſe, that <hi>Chriſt <hi>the</hi>
               </hi>
               <note n="b" place="margin">1. Pet. 1, 19</note> 
               <hi>innocent lambe of <hi>god,</hi>
               </hi> ſhould thus ſuffer for our redemption; verily to pacifie <hi>Gods</hi> wrath, and to ſatiſfie his iuſtice, who would not ſuffer the ſinne of man-kind vnpuniſhed in mankind Therfore it was expedient, that<note n="c" place="margin">1. Pet, 3, 18.</note> 
               <hi>the iuſt ſhould ſuffer for the</hi>
               <note n="d" place="margin">Ioh. 10.11,</note> 
               <hi>vniuſt, that the ſhepherd ſhould giue his life for his ſheep,</hi> that <hi>the <hi>Lord,</hi> ſhould redeem his people</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note n="*" place="margin">In the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice chriſt ſhineth, as in a merror, Gods wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome exten<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dyng his mer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cy, &amp; main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainyng his iuſtice.</note>O the vnſearchable wiſdome of <hi>God</hi> our gracious <hi>Lorde,</hi> whiche by
<pb facs="tcp:19080:44" rendition="simple:additions"/> the <hi>holines,</hi> and <hi>ſuffering</hi> of <hi>Chriſt</hi> his <hi>Sonne,</hi> hath both <hi>extended</hi> his <hi>mercy,</hi> and <hi>maintained</hi> his <hi>iuſtice:</hi> Extended his mercy,<note n="*" place="margin">1. Gods mercy exten<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ded</note> in forgiuing his elect their ſinnes, and that through Chriſts <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lines:</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">2. Gods iuſtice m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>in<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tained.</note> Mainteined his iuſtice, in puni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhing the nature of man, for the ſinnes of men, &amp; y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> through <hi>chriſts <hi>ſuffryng.</hi>
               </hi> And thus much concerning y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Second qualitie of the Sacrificer, which is the <hi>ſuffering</hi> of <hi>Chriſte</hi> our <hi>Lorde.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note n="*" place="margin">4, The ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice was offered for vs.</note>The fourth circumſtane in our re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption to bee obſerued, is, <hi>Who they are for whom this Sacrifice was offered <hi>Paule</hi>
               </hi> layeth that downe, when hee vſeth theſe wordes,<note n="a" place="margin">Eph, 5.2,</note> 
               <hi>For vs.</hi> In the wordes before, the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the <hi>Epheſians,</hi> to leade a godlie life, ſpeaketh vnto them in this man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner:<note n="b" place="margin">Eph. 5, 1,</note> 
               <hi>Bee yee folowers of God, as Children and walke yee in loue:</hi> but, deſcribing the manner of loue wherein we ſhould walke, by the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> he altereth the perſon ioyning himſelfe which wrote, with the <hi>Epheſians</hi> to whome hee wrote, and addeth,<note n="c." place="margin">5.2.</note> 
               <hi>Euen as chriſt hath lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued vs, and giuen himſelfe for vs.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:19080:44" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Hereby we learne that the beleeuing <hi>Iwes,</hi> as was the writer, and the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leuing <hi>Gentiles,</hi> as were they to whome the Epiſtle was written, are they for whom Chriſt offered himſelf.</p>
            <p>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Chriſt of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered for the beleeuyng, 1, Iewes 2. Gentiles.</note>But here more deepely muſt bee conſidered the ſtate and condition of both. And that ſhall we finde, when by <hi>Gods</hi> word we learne, what wee are by nature,<note n="*" place="margin">we are by nature the children of wrath,</note> 
               <note n="a" place="margin">Luc. 6.44.</note> the lances muſt bee ſuch, as is the tree:<note n="b" place="margin">Iam. 3.11.6</note> the ſurges muſt be ſuch, as is the fountaine. But <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam</hi>
               <note n="c" place="margin">Gen. 3.6</note> fallen from <hi>god</hi> by tranſgreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, is the tree from whence wee ſpring: <hi>Adam</hi>
               <note n="d" place="margin">3, 7.</note> ſtayned with ſinne, is the fountayne from whence wee ſlowe. So are wee by our parentage alienated from <hi>God,</hi> and ſtayned with ſinne,<note n="e" place="margin">Gen. 5.3.</note> being deſcended from <hi>Adam</hi> after his fall. Suche were wee for whome <hi>Chriſt</hi> gaue himſelfe. So many Sacrifices, being all figures of the ſacrifice of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> ordeined of <hi>god</hi> to bee<note n="f" place="margin">Leu. 4.2,</note> offered for the ſinnes of the people, do euidenly prooue that <hi>Gods</hi> people, for whome <hi>Chriſt</hi> was offered are all polluted with ſinne. It is true, that the auncient <hi>Iſraelites</hi> were gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uouſly<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               <pb facs="tcp:19080:45" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <note n="a" place="margin">Exo. 1.11. &amp;c,</note> oppreſſed in <hi>Aegipt</hi> by the tiranny of <hi>Pharao,</hi> &amp; from thence<note n="b" place="margin">Exod. 14.1,</note> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuered by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> commaundement of <hi>God,</hi> through the conduction of <hi>Moſes,</hi> but with all, therby is prefigured, that we bee all through ſinne, became ſlaues to <hi>Satan</hi> in this world, and through the wil of God, by the power of <hi>Chriſt</hi> deliuered from that ſpirituall capti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uitie. The <hi>Prophets, Chriſt,</hi> and the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> teache, that they, for whome <hi>Chriſt</hi> died, are<note n="c" place="margin">Rom. 5.8.</note> 
               <hi>steined</hi> with <hi>ſinne,</hi>
               <note n="d" place="margin">1. Tim. 1, 15</note> 
               <hi>tranſgreſſours</hi> of <hi>Gods <hi>lawe</hi>
               </hi>
               <note n="e" place="margin">Gal. 3, 13.</note> and <hi>ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect</hi> to his <hi>curſe. <hi>Eſaye</hi>
               </hi> propheciyng of our redemption, calleth vs<note n="f" place="margin">Eſa. 53, 4.</note> 
               <hi>weake,</hi>
               <note n="g" place="margin">53.5</note> 
               <hi>wounded,</hi> and <hi>ſinfull</hi>
               <note n="h" place="margin">53.6,</note>. <hi>Chriſt,</hi> ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of the ſame matter, pronounceth<note n="i" place="margin">Mat, 9, 12,</note> That <hi>the whole need not a phiſition, but they, that are ſicke:</hi>
               <note n="k" place="margin">Mat. 9.13,</note> And that <hi>hee came not, to call the righteous, but the ſinners to repentance.</hi> And <hi>Paule,</hi> ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of the accompliſhment of oure ſaluation, leaueth it thus recorded:<note n="l" place="margin">1. Tim, 1, 15</note> 
               <hi>This is a</hi> true <hi>ſaying, and by all means worthy to be receaued, that Chriſt Ieſus came into the world to ſaue ſinners,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note n="*" place="margin">That chriſt ſaueth ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, teacheh vs two things, our owne miſery 2 gods mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cye.</note>It may be, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſome wil demaund,
<pb facs="tcp:19080:45" rendition="simple:additions"/> why I vrge ſo greatly thys point. I anſwere: Chiefly for two cauſes.</p>
            <p>
               <note n="*" place="margin">1. our own miſery,</note>Firſt to teach vs, by acknowled<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging of our ſinnes,<note n="a" place="margin">Mat, 23, 12</note> to humble oure ſelues vnder the mightie hand of <hi>god</hi> that hee may aduaunce vs:<note n="b" place="margin">Ioh. 3.16</note> and to ſeeke vnto <hi>chriſt</hi> by fayth, that hee may deliuer vs: knowing that<note n="c" place="margin">11 32,</note> 
               <hi>God <hi>hath ſhut vppe all in vnbeliefe: that hee might haue mercy on all.</hi>
               </hi> And to this ende doth <hi>Paule</hi> diſpute mightily in the Epiſtle to the <hi>Romaines,</hi> prouing that,<note n="d" place="margin">Rom, 3, 20</note> 
               <hi>by the vvorkes of the law, no fleſh can be iuſtified in the ſight of <hi>God.</hi> But that,</hi>
               <note n="e" place="margin">24,</note> 
               <hi>wee are iustified freely by grace, through the redemption, that is in Chriſt concluding,</hi> that<note n="f" place="margin">28.</note> 
               <hi>a man is iustified by fayth without the workes of the law.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note n="*" place="margin">2, Gods mercy,</note>Then, to ſette before the eyes of our mindes, the exceeding meaſure of the loue of <hi>God</hi> towardes vs,<note n="g" place="margin">Io. 3, 16,</note> 
               <hi>which ſo loued the world, that</hi> he hath giuen his <hi>onely begotten <hi>Sonne,</hi> that whoſoeuer beleueth in him, ſhuld not periſh, but haue eternall life.</hi> But ſeeing<note n="h" place="margin">Rom, 5, 10</note> 
               <hi>God</hi> hath thus loued vs, <hi>when we were hys eni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, that he reconciled vs vnto himſelf, by the death of his <hi>Sonne,</hi> ought not we
<pb facs="tcp:19080:46" rendition="simple:additions"/> then</hi>
               <note n="a" place="margin">Eph, 5, 1,</note> 
               <hi>to be followers of <hi>god,</hi> as deare children,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2.</note> 
               <hi>and to walk in loue, as <hi>Chriſt</hi> hath loued vs, and giuen himſelfe for vs <hi>(to be)</hi> an offering and a ſacrifice of a ſweete ſmelling ſauour to <hi>god.</hi>
               </hi> Hetherto concerning the perſons, for whome <hi>chriſt</hi> died, euen for vs miſerable ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners.</p>
            <p>
               <note n="*" place="margin">5, This ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice was offered to God.</note>The fifth circumſtance, in our redemption diligently to bee conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, is <hi>vnto whome this holy ſacrifice was offered by <hi>Chriſt</hi> for our reconcilia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</hi> This doth <hi>Paule</hi> in this text eui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently ſhewe, when as hee teacheth, that it was offered<note n="b" place="margin">Eph, 5, 2,</note> to <hi>god.</hi> When parties at vnitie growe to diſcorde, then is there occaſion offered of recon<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ciliation, whiche cannot be accompli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed, but by the good diſcretion of a dayes-man, by whoſe meanes, the <hi>par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie offending</hi> is reconciled to the <hi>party offended.</hi> So ſtoode the caſe betweene <hi>god</hi> and <hi>man</hi> continued in that per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection,<note n="c" place="margin">Gen, 1, 26.</note> wherein <hi>God</hi> had created him.<note place="margin">5.27.</note> But when <hi>Man</hi> had tranſgreſſed the lawes of his <hi>God</hi>
               <note n="d" place="margin">Gen, 3, 6.7,</note> by eating of the forbidden fruite, then grew there diſcorde betweene <hi>God</hi> and <hi>Man
<pb facs="tcp:19080:46" rendition="simple:additions"/> Man</hi> the creature,<note place="margin">Man the party offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding God of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended,</note> became the <hi>partie offending:</hi> and <hi>God</hi> the <hi>creator,</hi> the <hi>partie offended.</hi> But ſuch was the peril of this falling out<note n="a" place="margin">Gen, 2, 17,</note> that <hi>Man</hi> became ſubiect to <hi>gods</hi> wrath and iudgment. Hence grewe the occaſion of an holy reconciliation, wherein the fauour of <hi>God</hi> onely, which was offended, was to be obtayned for <hi>Man</hi> onely, whiche had offended.<note place="margin">Chriſt the Dayeſman,</note> But what fit days-man could than be found to reconcile <hi>man</hi> vnto <hi>God?</hi> Onely <hi>Chriſt,</hi> both <hi>God</hi> &amp; <hi>ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,</hi> as more at large before I ſhewed. And how then? God woulde not, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> this reconciliation ſhould be wrought by diminiſhing y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> leaſt iote of his iuſtice.</p>
            <p>
               <note n="*" place="margin">The iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice of God conſidered in two pointes: 1, obedience, puniſhment.</note>Heerein ſtandeth the iuſtice of <hi>God,</hi> vrged by him in this reconcili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation. <hi>1. <hi>That mankinde keepe the lawe giuen:</hi> 2. <hi>That man-kinde be puniſhed for the law broken.</hi>
               </hi> And thus was hee affected, vnto whome the ſacrifice of pacification was, to be offered. Marke now y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> diſcretion of <hi>chriſt</hi> our dayes-man. In his <hi>Manhead</hi> hee<note n="b" place="margin">2, Cor. 5, 21</note> 
               <hi>obeyeth <hi>Gods</hi>
               </hi> lawes: In his <hi>man-head</hi> hee is<note n="c" place="margin">Pet, 2, 22,</note> 
               <hi>puniſhed</hi> for the breache of <hi>Gods</hi> lawes<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> hee obeyeth Gods
<pb facs="tcp:19080:47" rendition="simple:additions"/> law, by his innocent life:?<note n="*" place="margin">Obedience yelded by Chriſts inno<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cent life.</note> He is pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed for the breache of <hi>Gods</hi> lawe, by his <hi>dolorous death.</hi> By his <hi>obedience,</hi> he <hi>ſatiſfieth <hi>Gods</hi> iuſtice:</hi> By his <hi>ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring,</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">puniſhme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t ſuſtained by Chriſts do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lourous death.</note> he <hi>pacifieth <hi>Gods</hi> wrath.</hi> Thus did <hi>Chriſt</hi> our dayes-man offer himſelf obedient and patient, to <hi>God</hi> the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie offended, ſo to winne his fauour to <hi>Man</hi> the partie offending. By thys meanes <hi>Chriſt,</hi>
               <note n="a" place="margin">2, Cor, 5, 21</note> 
               <hi>which neuer commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted ſinne, made himſelfe to be reputed a ſinner for vs, that we which are ful of ſin, ſhould be reputed in him righteous before <hi>God.</hi>
               </hi> That,<note n="b" place="margin">Gal, 3.13</note> 
               <hi>he becomming accurſed for vs,</hi>
               <note place="margin">14</note> 
               <hi>we might become bleſſed tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rough him.</hi> So was it neceſſary, that vnto <hi>God</hi> this ſacrifice ſhoulde be of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered, that we therby vnto <hi>god</hi> might be reco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ciled. Of this point this much may ſuffice.</p>
            <p>
               <note n="*" place="margin">6: This ſacrifice wrought our full redemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</note>The ſixt and laſt circumſtance of our redemption, propoſed by <hi>Paule</hi> in this text to oure conſideration, ſheweth, <hi>vvhat effect this ſacrifice wrought, and vvhat ſucceſſe Chriſt had in this his attempt, thus to reco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cile man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kinde vnto <hi>god.</hi>
               </hi> This point is therfore the more deepely to bee conſidered
<pb facs="tcp:19080:47" rendition="simple:additions"/> becauſe therein eyther is the <hi>riſing</hi> againe into <hi>conſolation,</hi> or the <hi>down<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fall</hi> into <hi>deſperation.</hi> For, if <hi>Chriſt <hi>preuailed</hi>
               </hi> in this his mediation, then are wee <hi>ſaued:</hi> but if hee <hi>fayled,</hi> then are wee <hi>damned. <hi>Paule</hi>
               </hi> therefore to heale the wounde of the conſcience pearced with ſin, concludeth, that this Sacrifice, thus offered by <hi>Chriſt,</hi> yeel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded,<note n="a" place="margin">Eph. 5:2:</note> 
               <hi>as a ſweete ſmelling ſauoure in the noſe-therles of <hi>God.</hi>
               </hi> By this metapho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ricall ſpeach borrowed from the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of offering incenſe, and burnt Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifices the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> ſheweth, that<note n="b" place="margin">Eſa: 53, 10</note> 
               <hi>the deuiſe of the <hi>Lorde</hi> proſpered in the hand of <hi>Chriſt:</hi>
               </hi> That is to ſay, that<note n="c" place="margin">Gen 3, 15</note> 
               <hi>Chriſt <hi>the ſeed of the woman hath troa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den downe the head of the Serpent:</hi>
               </hi> That<note n="d" place="margin">Heb, 10, 14</note> 
               <hi>chriſt <hi>our high prieſt, with this his one offering, hath conſecrated vs for euer, vnto</hi> God, <hi>whiche are ſanctified:</hi>
               </hi> That<note place="margin">Gal, 3.13</note> 
               <hi>Chriſt <hi>hath redeemed vs from the curſe of the lawe</hi>
               </hi>
               <note n="f" place="margin">Deu: 21:23:</note> 
               <hi>being him ſelfe made a curſe for vs: That</hi>
               <note n="g" place="margin">Heb: 10:16</note> 
               <hi>the Lord in the bloud of his ſon hath made with vs his elect his new couenaunt: that he will put his lawes in our heartes, and write them in our mindes:</hi>
               <note place="margin">17,</note> And that <hi>hee will remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber
<pb facs="tcp:19080:48" rendition="simple:additions"/> no more our ſinnes and iniquities.</hi> And this is the mightie effect of the gracious reconciliation mercifully vndertaken, &amp; wonderfully accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſhed by <hi>Chriſt</hi> our <hi>Lord. I</hi> ſhewed before that the oblations and Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices of the old lawe were all figures of the Sacrifice of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and their <hi>Prieſt-hood</hi> a ſine of his <hi>prieſt-hood</hi> Then muſt it proportionably follow,<note place="margin">The accepta<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of chriſts ſacrifice figu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>red in the approbation of the obla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions &amp; ſacri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fices of the Fathers,</note> that the acceptation of their ſacrifices before <hi>god,</hi> was alſo a figure of the allowance of the ſacrifice of <hi>Chriſt.</hi>
               <note n="a" place="margin">Gen: 4.4.</note> So had the <hi>Lorde</hi> in ancient time <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect</hi> vnto <hi>Habell and vnto his oblation,</hi>
               <note n="b" place="margin">Heb. 11:4:</note> inſomuch that <hi>god</hi> himſelf <hi>teſtified of his giftes.</hi>
               <note n="c" place="margin">Gen. 8.21.</note> So did the <hi>Lord <hi>ſmell a ſweete fauour from the vvhole burnt of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering of</hi> Noah, <hi>after the floud, offered vpon the alter.</hi>
               </hi>
               <note n="d" place="margin">Leu. 9.24. 2. Chro. 7, 1.</note> So did the <hi>Lorde</hi> eftſoones ſend down fire from heauen which conſumed the burnt offeringes and the ſacrifices, whiche in his lawe he had appointed to be offered to him. What ſhall wee thinke? Doth the Lord delight in bulles fleſh, and in the bloud of goates?<note n="e" place="margin">Pſal. 5, 8, 9.10.11, 12.13.</note> No: But the <hi>Lord</hi> our <hi>god,</hi> by accepting theſe ſacrifices,
<pb facs="tcp:19080:48" rendition="simple:additions"/> prefigureth the allowance before hys maieſty, of the ſacrifice of <hi>Ieſus chriſt</hi> whereof theſe were ſhadowes and fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gures, as before I ſayde. Thus was<note n="a" place="margin">Heb. i9.28.</note> 
               <hi>Chriſt once offred to take away the ſins of many,</hi>
               <note place="margin">24,</note> 
               <hi>&amp; is entred into the very heauens to appeare novv in the ſight of <hi>god</hi> for vs:</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">26.</note> 
               <hi>vvho, by the ſacrifice of himſelfe, hath put avvaye ſinne,</hi>
               <note n="b" place="margin">Pſal, 110.4. Heb. 5.6.</note> 
               <hi>remaining a prieſt for euer after the order of <hi>Mel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiſedech:</hi> and is ſet dovvn at the right hand of <hi>god</hi> the Father in povver and glorie</hi>
               <note n="c" place="margin">Pſal. 110.1. Mat. 22.44.</note> 
               <hi>vntill his enemies be made hys foot-ſtoole.</hi> And this much concerning the laſt point of our redemption.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The conclu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſion exhorta<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tory.</note>
               <hi>Seeing threfore, brethren</hi> (that I may conclude the whole with the wordes of holy ſcripture) <hi>that by the bloud of Ieſus vve may be bold to enter into the holy place,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Heb. 10.19,</note> 
               <hi>By the nevv and li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing vvay,</hi>
               <note place="margin">20.</note> 
               <hi>vvhich he hath prepared for vs, through the vayle, that is his fleſhe (And ſeeing vve haue)</hi> an high Prieſt <hi>vvhich is ouer the houſe of <hi>god,</hi>
               </hi>
               <note place="margin">21,</note> 
               <hi>let vs dravv neere vvith a true heart,</hi>
               <note place="margin">22,</note> 
               <hi>in aſſurance of fayth, our hearts being pure from an euill conſcience,</hi>
               <note place="margin">23.</note> 
               <hi>And vvaſhed in our bodies vvith pure vvater let vs
<pb facs="tcp:19080:49" rendition="simple:additions"/> keep the profeſsion of our hope, vvithout vvauering, (for (he is) faythfull that promiſed). And let vs conſider one an other,</hi>
               <note place="margin">24.</note> 
               <hi>to prouoke vnto loue, and to good vvorkes.. Not forſaking the fellovv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip,</hi>
               <note place="margin">25,</note> 
               <hi>that vve haue among our ſelues, as the manner of ſome is, but let vs exhort one an other, &amp; ſo much the more, becauſe ye ſee that the day draweth neer,</hi> So ſhal we be followers of god, as deere chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, and walk in loue, euen as <hi>Chriſt</hi> hath loued vs,<note n="*" place="margin">Eph. 5.1.2</note> and giuen him ſelf for vs, to be an offering and a ſacrifice of a ſweet ſmelling ſauour to <hi>god</hi> which the <hi>Father</hi> of heauen, and the <hi>god</hi> of all mercy worke in our hearts for <hi>Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus chriſtes</hi> ſake, by the operation of his <hi>holy ſpirit,</hi> vnto whom, <hi>father ſon</hi> and <hi>holy ghoſt,</hi> three perſons and one true, omnipotent, gracious, glorious, and eternal <hi>god</hi> be al honour and glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, prayſe, power, and dominion for euer. <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>¶FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:19080:49"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
